<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The layman's ritual containing practical methods of Christian duties both religious and moral drawn out of H. Scripture, the Roman ritual, the catechism ad parchos &amp;c. / by C.T.</title>
            <author>Tootell, Christopher, ca. 1660-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28200</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10445807</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10445807</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45075</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62950)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45075)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1390:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The layman's ritual containing practical methods of Christian duties both religious and moral drawn out of H. Scripture, the Roman ritual, the catechism ad parchos &amp;c. / by C.T.</title>
                  <author>Tootell, Christopher, ca. 1660-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 174 [i.e. 172] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Christopher Tootel.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Catholic authors.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45075:1"/>
            <p>THE LAY-MAN's <hi>Ritual:</hi> CONTAINING, Practical Methods of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duties, both Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Moral; Drawn out of H. Scripture, the <hi>Roman</hi> Ritual, the Catechiſm <hi>ad Parochos,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>C. T.</hi> Clergy-man; For the Inſtruction of his FLOCK.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let all things be done decently, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to order,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 14.40.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:45075:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45075:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the following Work, I have endeavour'd (for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Reaſons,) to crowd great ſtore of Matter in a little room, yet ſo as to render the Duties it Treats of, as intelligible and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar as poſſibly I could, in few Words: Nevertheleſs, Obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is ſo eſſential to Brevity, that I cannot expect, but you'll ſtand in need of an Interpreter, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places; and therefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb facs="tcp:45075:3"/>you very frequently to other Books, handling more largely what I deliver in ſhort: If you have them not by you, then recur to your Spiritual Director for the Explication of what you do not underſtand. By this means, the Whole will be ſerviceable to you; eſpecially, if you read it often, and make it the Rule of your Religious and Moral Actions, in order to pleaſe God in all you do. This is the Noble End it aims at: Towards obtaining whereof, I wiſh it may prove uſeful to Many, humbly deſiring All that are benefitted by my poor Endeavours, to ſay a <hi>Pater</hi> and an <hi>Ave</hi> for my Intention.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:45075:3"/>
            <head>A TABLE Of the following Chapters, and their Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ch. I. Of Baptiſm.</item>
               <item>Ch. II. Of Confirmation.</item>
               <item>Ch. III. Of Penance.</item>
               <item>Ch. IV. Of Indulgences.</item>
               <item>Ch. V. Of H. Communion.</item>
               <item>Ch. VI. Of Communion of the Sick.</item>
               <item>Ch. VII. Of Receiving our <hi>Via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ch. VIII. Of How often the H. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt is to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd.</item>
               <item>Ch. IX. Of Extreme-Unction.</item>
               <item>Ch. X. Of H. Orders.</item>
               <item>Ch. XI. Of Matrimony.</item>
               <item>Ch. XII. Of Of Churching Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men after Child-Birth.</item>
               <item>Ch. XIII. Of Prayer.</item>
               <item>Ch. XIV. Of Hearing Maſs.</item>
               <item>Ch. XV. Of Hearing Sermons.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:45075:4"/>
               <item>Ch. XVI. Of Reading Pious Books.</item>
               <item>Ch. XVII. Of H. Proceſſions.</item>
               <item>Ch. XVIII. Of Viſiting the Sick.</item>
               <item>Ch. XIX. Of Aſſiſting Dying Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</item>
               <item>Ch. XX. Of Burying the Dead.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXI. Of Alms-giving.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXII. Of Faſting.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXIII. Of Holy-Day-Duties.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXIV. Of Working and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXV. Of Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXVI. Of Diſcourſe.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXVII. Of Recreation.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXVIII. Of Family-Duties.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXIX. Of A Morning-Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</item>
               <item>Ch. XXX. Of An Evening-Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</item>
               <item>Ch. Of The Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45075:4"/>THE LAY-MAN's <hi>Ritual.</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of</hi> Baptiſm.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Chriſt loved the Church, and deliver'd himſelf for it; that he might ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it, cleanſing it with the Laver of Water in the Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               </q>
               <bibl>Eph. <hi>5.25. &amp;c.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HOLY BAPTISM, the Gate (or Entrance) of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and of Life Everlaſting, holds the firſt Place amongſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the New Law, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45075:5"/>by Chriſt; and it is neceſſary for the Salvation of all Mankind, as Truth it ſelf witneſſes in theſe Words: <hi>Niſi quis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs a Man be born again of Water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jo. 3.5.</note> Therefore extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Diligence is to be uſed in the timely and due Adminiſtration and Receiving of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>And tho' the Solemn Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Baptiſm belongs to the Clergy, nevertheleſs, as often as an Infant, or any other Perſon unbaptized, is in danger of Death, ſuch an one, may and ought to be baptized Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately by any Laick, and in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage whatever, provided the Form and Intention of the Church be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd and kept.</p>
            <p>But where Choice may be had, one of the Faithful is to be preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an Infidel, a Catholick before a Heretick, any other Cath. before the Child's Father or Mother, a Man before a Woman, except the Child is to be baptized, whilſt the Mother is in Labor, or unleſs the Woman
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45075:5"/>knows the Form and Manner of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, better than the Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence, all the Faithful, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Midwives, ought to know how to Baptize aright: Which is after this manner;</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> They muſt pour or ſprinkle Natural Water upon ſome part of the Child, and at the ſame time ſay: <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> 
               <hi>I baptize thee in the Name of the Father and of the Son, and of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt:</hi> And this they muſt do and ſay with an Intention to make the Infant a Chriſtian, and Member of Chriſt's Church.</p>
            <p>Tho' the Church baptizes Infants and Idiots in the Faith of their God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers, without their actual Knowledge and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence; nevertheleſs more is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſuch, as are come to the uſe of Reaſon, not only Before, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo In, and After Baptiſm. And,</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. I. <hi>Before</hi> Baptiſm.</head>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt be well Inſtructed in the Faith and Law of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45075:6"/>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt Believe expreſly what is taught them, renouncing all former Infidelity. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.36. &amp;c. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 31. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt have hearty Sorrow for their Sins, with Purpoſes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37, 38. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They muſt exerciſe themſelves, ſome Days before, in Works of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And it is meet they ſhould be Faſting, when they are Baptized.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. II. <hi>At</hi> Baptiſm.</head>
               <p>Let them Conſider how, <hi>when Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was Baptized of</hi> John <hi>in</hi> Jordan, <hi>the Heavens open'd to him; and the Holy Ghoſt deſcended in Corporal Shape as a Dove, and remain'd upon him: And a Voice was made from Heaven, ſaying, Thou art my beloved Son; in thee I am well pleaſed.</hi> Mar. 1. Luk. 3.</p>
               <p>And hence let them gather the happy Effects of Baptiſm: In ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whereof, 1. The Gates of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhut againſt Sinners, <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Apoc. 21.27.</note> are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45075:6"/>open'd to them. 2. The H. Ghoſt deſcends upon them,
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Tit. 3.5, 6.</note> making them in Innocence like Doves,
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Mat. 10.16.</note>. 3. They are made the Adopted Children of God, and Heirs apparent to the Kingdom of Heaven, <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Tit. 3.7.</note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. III. <hi>After</hi> Baptiſm.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Let them thankfully reflect upon the happy Change made in their Souls by means of Baptiſm, and ſay, <hi>We were by Nature the Children of Wrath, as alſo the reſt</hi> [of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind:] <hi>But God (who is rich in Mercy) for his exceeding Charity, wherewith he loved us, even when we were dead by Sins, quickned us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Thanks be to God the Father, who has made us worthy unto a part of the Lot of the Saints</hi> [or the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful] <hi>in the Light; who has deliver'd us from the Power of Darkneſs, and has tranſlated us into the Kingdom</hi> [or Church] <hi>of his beloved Son, in whom
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45075:7"/>we have Redemption, the Remiſſion of Sins. This is the Change of the right Hand of the Higheſt.</hi> Col. 1.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pſ. 76.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Night</hi> [of Sin] <hi>is paſt, the Day</hi> [of Grace] <hi>is at hand; let us therefore caſt off the Works of Darkneſs, and put on the Armor of Light: As in the Day</hi>
[of Grace,] <hi>let us walk honeſtly; not in Banquettings and Drunkenneſs, not in Chamberings and Impudicities, not in Contention and Emulation; but put ye on our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And according to him, who has called you the Holy One,</hi> [that is, according to Chriſt,] <hi>be you alſo in all Converſation Holy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. &amp;c. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. See alſo, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Now tho' the Sacrament of Baptiſm and Remiſſion of Sins thereby can be received no more than once, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet the Memory of ſo great a Benefit, both may and ought frequently to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd as long as we live on Earth: Therefore mark well the <hi>Manner</hi> and the <hi>Time</hi> of diſcharging this Duty. And,</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45075:7"/>
               <p>§. 1. As to the <hi>Manner:</hi> You are to conſider the Happy Effects and Wonderful Change wrought in your Souls by Baptiſm; the perfect State of Grace and Innocence to which it reſtor'd you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, §. II. and §. III. N. 1. and 2.</p>
               <p>Next, Look narrowly into the preſent State of your guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſay,
<note place="margin">Jer. 9.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Who will give Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to my Head, and to my Eyes a Fountain of Tears? And I will weep Day and Night;</hi> for that (both Day and Night) I have broken the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made for me at the Font; I have forſaken God to take part with the Devil, his Works, and Pomps, by me ſo ſolemnly there renounced; I have ſtain'd the White Robe of Innocence there given me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then Sprinkle your ſelf with the Holy Water, in remembrance of Chriſt's Baptiſm, and of your own Regeneration, wiſhing you could revive in your Soul the Grace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by received, and ſay, <note place="margin">Job 29.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Who will grant me, that I may be according to former Months, according to the Days in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45075:8"/>which God kept me? When his Lamp ſhined over my Head,</hi> &amp;c. the Prieſt ſaying to me, <hi>Accipe Lampadem ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou, Lord, ſhall ſprinkle me with Hyſop,</hi> [Contrition and Sorrow for my Sins] <hi>and I ſhall be cleanſed: Thou ſhalt waſh me</hi> [in the Baptiſm of Penance, or Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Tears,] <hi>and I ſhall be made whiter than Snow,</hi> Pſ. 50.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Exhort your ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to comply more faithfully with the Obligations of a Chriſtian, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before, §. III. <hi>N.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>§. II. As to the <hi>Time:</hi> It may be done moſt properly, 1. On the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phany,</hi> or <hi>Twelf-Day;</hi> when the Church makes a Commemoration of Chriſt's Baptiſm. 2. On <hi>Eaſter-Eve,</hi> and <hi>Whitſun-Eve;</hi> thoſe being Days appointed by the Church for Hallowing of the Font, and for the Solemn Baptiſm of Catechumens, or Unbaptized Converts. 3. On the <hi>Anniverſary-Day</hi> of your own Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, or on the <hi>Saints-Day</hi> whoſe Name you bear. 4. As often as you chance to be preſent at the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45075:8"/>of this Sacrament. 5. As often as you take H. Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of</hi> Confirmation.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>He that Confirms us with you in Chriſt, and he that has Anointed us, <hi>[is]</hi> God: Who alſo has Sealed us <hi>[with a Spiritual Character,]</hi> and has given the Pledge of his Spirit in our Hearts, </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 1.21, 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>COnfirmation is a Sacrament of the Goſpel; in which, after Baptiſm, we receive the Holy Ghoſt <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Act. 8.14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> c. 19. v. 5, 6.</note>, and are made perfect Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; <hi>becauſe the Charity of God is pour'd forth in our Hearts, by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, who is given us, <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Rom. 5.5.</note>. And in like manner alſo, the Spirit helps our Infirmity</hi> 
               <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Rom. 8.26.</note>, to overcome all Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in the Profeſſion and Practice
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45075:9"/>of Chriſtianity, <hi>that neither Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor Perſecution, nor Death, nor any Creature may be able to ſeparate us from the Charity of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord,</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi> v. 35, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>Now, that ſuch as are come to the Uſe of Reaſon, may receive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Vertue, Grace, and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, by means of this Sacrament, They muſt obſerve (Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, At, and After Confirmation,) what follows. And,</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1. <hi>Before</hi> Confirmation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. They muſt be well inſtructed and made ſenſible of the Neceſſity and Vertue of this Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They muſt put themſelves in the State of Grace, by going firſt to Confeſſion, with all the Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Soul truly Penitent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted: Becauſe <hi>Wiſdom</hi>
[with the reſt of the Gifts <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 11.2.</note> of the Holy Ghoſt] <hi>will not enter into a malicious Soul, nor dwell in a Body ſubject to Sin,</hi> Wiſ. 1.4.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:45075:9"/>
               <p n="3">3. They muſt give themſelves (ſome time before) to holy Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and fervent Prayer, in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles: Who, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to receive the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>went into an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Room; where all of them were perſevering with one Mind in Prayer,</hi> Act. 1.13, 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pray</hi> therefore <hi>with bended Knees, to the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that he give you (according to the Riches of his Glory,) Power to be ſtrengthned by his Spirit, in the inner Man,</hi> Eph. 3.14, 16. And, for that end, ſay the Hymns, <hi>Vent Creator Spiritus, &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>Veni Sancie Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus, &amp;c.</hi> with the <hi>Office of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as in the <hi>Manual</hi> and <hi>Primer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The laudable Cuſtom of the Church, requires, that Healthful People of riper Years receive this Sacrament Faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. II. <hi>At</hi> Confirmation.</head>
               <p>Whilſt the Biſhop anoils your Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head with H. Chriſm, in form of a Croſs, [ſaying, <hi>I Sign thee with the Sign of the Croſs; I Confirm thee with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45075:10"/>the Chriſm of Salvation, In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>] and gives you a light <hi>Blow</hi> on the Cheek, ſaying, <hi>Peace be with thee.</hi> Reflect how by theſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Proceedings, you are made the <hi>Soldier</hi> of Chriſt; whoſe <hi>Standard</hi> is the Croſs <note n="(i)" place="bottom">Mat. 24.30.</note>, whoſe <hi>Armor</hi> is the Armor of God; to wit, the Helmet of Hope, the Breaſt-plate and Shield of Faith, Charity and Juſtice, the Girdle of Continency and Truth, the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note n="(k)" place="bottom">Eph. 6.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.8. Heb. 4.12. 1 Pet. 1.13.</note>, whoſe <hi>Enemies</hi> are the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; who are ſure to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front them with repeated <hi>Blows,</hi> that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, <note n="(l)" place="bottom">2 Tim. 3.12.</note>. But <hi>thou, Lord, wilt give Peace to us,</hi> 
                  <note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.12.</note>; and, <hi>there is much Peace to them that love thy Law</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118.165.</note>, even amidſt their greateſt Sufferings, <note n="(o)" place="bottom">Jo. 16.33. 2 Cor. 4.8.9, 16. c. 6. v. 9, 10. c. 7. v. 4.</note>: <hi>For, whereas Wickedneſs is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45075:10"/>fearful, it gives Teſtimony of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> [againſt it ſelf]: <hi>For, a a troubled Conſcience do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume cruel Things,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(p)" place="bottom">Wiſ. 17.10.</note> But, <hi>a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Mind</hi> [the effect of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,] <hi>is, as it were, a continual Feaſt,</hi> Prov. 15.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. III. <hi>After</hi> Confirmation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Let every one imagine, a Voice from Heaven ſays to him: <hi>Thou therefore be ſtrong in the Grace, which is in Chriſt Jeſus: — Labour thou, as a good Soldier of Chriſt Jeſus: — For he that ſtrives for the Maſtery, is not Crown'd, unleſs he ſtrives lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Dread not at ſudden Terror, and the Power of the wicked Falling upon thee: For our Lord will be at thy ſide, and will keep thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t, that thou be not taken. Fear none of thoſe things, which thou ſhalt ſuffer: — Be thou faithful until Death, and Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus will g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> thee the Crown of Life.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.1. Prov. 3.25. Apoc. 2.10. <hi>See alſo,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.7, 8.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45075:11"/>
               <p n="2">2. Give Thanks to God, for that <hi>your Members are the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, who is in you, whom you have of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Reſolve to take the Apoſtles Advice, who ſays, <hi>Give not place to to the Devil,—and contriſtate not</hi> [by Sin] <hi>the Holy Spirit of God, in which you are Signed unto the Day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. For you</hi> [that are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd and Confirm'd,] <hi>are the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and the Spirit of God dwells in you: But if any one violate the Temple of God, God will deſtroy him: For the Temple of God is Holy, which you are.</hi> Eph. 4.27, 30. 1 Cor. 3.16, 17.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Be ſure to ſtay till the Biſhop's Benediction be given: And whilſt he gives it, ſay, <hi>The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Charity of God, and the Communication of the Holy Ghoſt, be with</hi> us <hi>all.</hi> Amen. 2 Cor. 13.13.</p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Tho' the Sacrament of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation can be Receiv'd no more than once, yet the Grace it gives may be revived in your Soul, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45075:11"/>its Obligations may be reinforced, when you pleaſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By Examining, How you have complied with the Duties incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on ſuch as are Confirm'd, and whether you have play'd the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion or Coward, under the Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of the Croſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By heartily lamenting the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times you have traiterouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted Chriſt Jeſus, in compliance with the World, the Fleſh, or the Devil.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By renewing your Purpoſe, of Fighting Couragiouſly, and Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even to Blood and Death it ſelf, rather than yield to Sin any more. And,</p>
               <p n="4">4. By Praying earneſtly for the Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, that <hi>henceforth</hi> you may <hi>be ſtrengthned in our Lord, and in the Might of his Power,</hi> ſo as to <hi>ſtand</hi> againſt your Ghoſtly Enemies <hi>in all things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> Eph. 6.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this Exerciſe may be very profitably uſed:</p>
               <p n="1">1. On <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45075:12"/>were Confirm'd after an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. On the <hi>Anniverſary-day</hi> of your own Confirmation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As aften as you are preſent at the Adminiſtration of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As often as any violent Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or Perſecution threatens you.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As often as you have had the Misfortune to fall into any grievous Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of</hi> Penance.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Convert, and do Penance from all your Iniquities; and Iniquity ſhall not be a Ruin to you,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Ezek. 18.30.</hi>
                  </bibl> See
<bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 13.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE H. Sacrament of Penance (inſtituted by Chriſt our Lord, <note n="*" place="margin">Jo. 20.22, 23.</note> for reſtoring to the Grace of God, thoſe who are fallen into Sin after
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45075:12"/>Baptiſm,) has Three Parts: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, Confeſſion, and Satisfaction: All which (every time you come to this Sacrament,) ought to be as fully perform'd, as if you were to Die ſoon after, and were to have no other opportunity of Reconciliation to God.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1. <hi>Of</hi> Contrition.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Beg Light to know, and Grace to rectifie the Evil State of your Conſcience; ſaying, <hi>My God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten my Darkneſs, <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Pſ. 17.29.</note>: How great Iniquities and Sins have I, my wicked Deeds and my Offences ſhew thou me,</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Job 13.23.</note>. 'Tis for want of thy Light, that <hi>the Way of the Wicked is darkſom; they know not where they fall,</hi> 
                  <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Prov. 4.19.</note>. And, <hi>there is a Way which to a Man ſeems juſt, and right; but the latter ends thereof, lead to Death, <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Prov. 14.12. c. 16. v. 25.</note>. Regard</hi> therefore, <hi>and hear me,</hi> O Lord, my God: <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten my Eyes, that I ſleep not in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45075:13"/>Death,</hi> [or, deadly Sin,] <hi>at any time; leſt ſometime my Enemy ſay, I have prevail'd againſt him, <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Pſ. 12.4, 5.</note>; leſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time He, as a Lion, violently take my Soul, whilſt there is none to redeem, or ſave it,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Pſ. 7.3.</note>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Examine your Conſcience di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, by conſidering when it was you made your laſt Confeſſion, and whether you then left not ſome deadly Sin unconfeſſed, either pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, or thro' negligence in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining your ſelf, whether you were not Deficient in Sorrow for your Sins, or in Purpoſes of Amendment, and whether you fulfilled the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance enjoin'd you? Becauſe, if at any time, your Confeſſion, Sorrow, or Purpoſes, have been inſincere, they muſt all be renew'd and made over again: But, if you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied faithfully with theſe Duties of Penance, give Thanks to God, and then proceed in Examining, how you behaved your ſelf at your laſt Communion; and, from that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45075:13"/>time till this preſent, Reflect, what Places and Company you have been in? What Employments you have follow'd, and how you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> your ſelf therein towards God, your Self, and your Neighbor, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Words, and Deeds? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of your Underſtanding, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> What Miſgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of your Senſes, in Seeing, Hearing, Smelling, Taſting, Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of your Duty, in not doing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and in not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Evil, according to your Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Obligation? What Sins you are moſt inclined unto, and moſt accuſtomed to commit? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And you muſt weigh each Sin, you find your ſelf guilty of, in all its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> by conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Quality of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> as to your ſelf offending, and as to thoſe, with whom, and againſt whom, you offended; the Importance of the <hi>Matter,</hi> about which you tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed; the Length of the <hi>Time,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45075:14"/>the Holineſs of the <hi>Place</hi> in which you ſigned; the <hi>Intention,</hi> you had, or End you aim'd at; the <hi>Means,</hi> you uſed; the <hi>Manner,</hi> with which you acted; the <hi>Number</hi> of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes into the ſame Sin; the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> and <hi>Scandal</hi> or ill Example that follow'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And beſure to mark well the <hi>Occasions</hi> you took, or gave others, of falling into any great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that you may avoid them for the future. And when you have an Examination to make of a whole Month or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> time, you may help your Memory, by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſing the Table of Sins in the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But thoſe, that <hi>ſtudy to have a Conſcience without Offence towards God, and towards Men always,</hi> Acts 24.16. and are accuſtom'd to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min themſelves daily and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs often, need no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Helps for calling to Mind the Sins they have to confeſs, beſides a moderate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the Obſervation they made in their Daily Examinations. An eaſie Task, in compariſon of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45075:14"/>what they have to do, who neglect thoſe frequent Inſpections into their Conſcience, and go ſeldom to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Short half-made Accompts are ſumm'd up, and adjuſted with leſs Labor, and more Exactneſs, tham long Intricate Reckonings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Having found out the Nature and Number of your Sinful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions and Omiſſions, abhor and deteſt them all in general <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 118.163.</note>, and thoſe in particular, which ſeem moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normous, and into which you fall moſt frequently: Deteſt them, I ſay, with hearty Sorrow, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Love of God, and with a firm Purpoſe to do Penance for what's paſt, and to Amend for the future, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>you ſhall call to Mind your Ways, and all your wicked Deeds, in which you were polluted: And you ſhall miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke your ſelves in your own ſight, in all the Malices which you have done: And when thou ſhalt ſeek the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt find him: Yet ſo, if thou ſeek'ſt him with all thy Heart, and all the Tribulation
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45075:15"/>of thy Soul.</hi> For, <hi>a Sacrifice to God is an Afflicted Spirit: A Contrite and an Humbled Heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> Ezek. 20.43. Deut. 4.29. Pſal. 50.19.</p>
               <p>But this Sorrow for Sins paſt muſt proceed from the Love of God, and not from any Worldly Reſpect; becauſe, <hi>The Sorrow of the World works Death, and kills many, and there is no Profit in it: But the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that is according to God, works Penance unto Salvation, that is ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt.</hi> Ecclus 30.25. 2 Cor. 7.10.</p>
               <p>Such was the Sorrow of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> when ſhe water'd Chriſt's Feet with Penitential Tears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in regard wherof, Jeſus ſaid to <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Many Sins are forgiven her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe has loved much. But to whom leſs is forgiven, he loves leſs.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 7.38. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Whence S. <hi>John</hi> concludes, <hi>He that loves not, abides in Death;</hi> that is, in Deadly Sin unforgiven, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:45075:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us therefore love God,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(a)" place="bottom">1 John 4.19.</note> And <hi>you that love our Lord, hate ye Evil.</hi> 
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Pſal. 96.10.</note> Becauſe <hi>He that loves God,</hi> [and hates Sin] <hi>praying, ſhall obtain</hi> [Pardon] <hi>for Sins, and ſhall</hi> [not only purpoſe Amendment, but alſo effectually] <hi>refrain himſelf from them.</hi> Ecclus 3.4.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Make the following <hi>Act of Contrition</hi> in all Sincerity, and with the Sentiments of a Heart, truly Penitent.</p>
               <p>My God and my All, I deteſt all [and eſpecially <hi>ſuch and ſuch</hi>] Sins of my Life paſt, above all things deteſtable. I am ſorry from my very Heart, and I wiſh I were more ſorrowful, for that I (an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Wretch) have offended thee, whom I ought to have loved above all things. I firmly purpoſe by thy Holy Grace, to confeſs my Sins faithfully, and to do the Penance that ſhall be enjoin'd me for the ſame; as alſo to avoid all [and eſpecially <hi>ſuch and ſuch</hi>] Occaſions
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45075:16"/>of Sin, and never to offend thee more. And in Satisfaction for my paſt Offences I offer unto thee, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Actions and Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Chriſt, all the Good I have done, or ſhall do, and all the Evil I have ſuffer'd, or ſhall ſuffer; hoping thou wilt accept thereof, and pardon me for thy Mercies ſake, and the Merits of thy only Son, out Dear Redeemer, Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And (that you may nor be too remiſs in a Duty that requires Pains <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 6.7.</note>) for farther Improvement of your Sorrow, read in the Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs of your Soul the <hi>Pſalm Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere,</hi> with the following <hi>Prayer of Manaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Lord Omnipotent, who didſt make Heaven and Earth, with all their Ornaments, who haſt bound the Sea with the Word of thy Precept, whom all things Dread and Tremble at the Viſage of thy Power, becauſe the Magnificence of thy Glory is not Supportable, and and the Wrath of thy Threatning upon Sinners is Intolerable; but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45075:16"/>the Mercy of thy Promiſe is Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and unſeachable; becauſe thou art our Lord, moſt High, Benign, Long-ſuffering, very Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, and Penitent, upon the Wickedneſs of Men. Thou, Lord, according to the Multitude of thy Goodneſs, haſt promiſed Penance and Remiſſion to them that have ſinned to thee, and in the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy Mercies, thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed Penance for Sinners unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Thou, therefore, Lord God of the Juſt, haſt not appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Penance for the Juſt, and them that have not ſinned to thee, but haſt appointed Penance for me, a Sinner: Becauſe I have ſinned above the number of the Sands of the Sea: My Iniquities, Lord, are multiplied, my Iniquities are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, and I am not worthy to behold and look upon the height of Heaven for the Multitude of my Iniquities. I am made crooked with many a Band [of Sinful Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Habits] that I cannot lift up my Head, and I have no Reſpit:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45075:17"/>Becauſe I have ſtin'd up thy Wrath, and have done Evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee: I have not done thy Will, and thy Commandments I have not kept: I have ſet up A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations, and I have multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Offences. And now I bow the Knee of my Heart, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Goodneſs of thee. I have ſinned, Lord, I have ſinned, and I acknowledge my Iniquities. Wherefore I petition, beſeeching thee, Forgive me, Lord, forgive me, and deſtroy me not together with my Iniquities, neither reſerve thou for ever, in thy Wrath, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils for me, neither Damn thou me in the loweſt Places of the Earth: Becauſe thou art God, God, I ſay, of the Penitent; and in me thou ſhalt ſhew all thy Goodneſs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou ſhalt ſave me, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, according to thy great Mercy; and I will praiſe thee always, all the Days of my Life: Becauſe all the Power of the Heavens praiſes thee, and to thee is Glory for ever and ever.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:45075:17"/>
               <p n="5">5. Say the <hi>Prayer before Confeſſion,</hi> as in the <hi>Manual,</hi> or <hi>Primer,</hi> and then <hi>Go, ſhew your ſelves to the Prieſts</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 17.14.</note>, to whom <hi>God has given the Miniſtry of Reconciliation</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18.</note>, in vertue of Chriſt's Commiſſion, <hi>viz. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ye the Holy Ghoſt: Whoſe Sins you ſhall forgive, they are forgiven them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.23. See alſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§ II. <hi>Of</hi> Confeſſion.</head>
               <p>Place your ſelf on your Knees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide Chriſt's Miniſter, (like <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> at Chriſt's Feet, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38.) make the Sign of the Croſs, ask Bleſſing, and (it being given) ſay: <hi>I confeſs to Almighty God — and to you, Father, that I have very much ſinned in Thought, Word, and Deed, thro' my Fault, thro' my Fault, thro' my moſt grievous Fault:</hi> Knocking your Breaſt (with the Humble Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.13.) thrice, whilſt you ſay, <hi>Thro' my Fault,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then (having firſt acquainted your <hi>Confeſſarius</hi> with your State and Calling, if he knows it not)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45075:18"/>begin your Confeſſion thus: <hi>I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my ſelf, that ſince my laſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion (which was ſo many Days, Weeks, or Months ago) I have</hi> —</p>
               <p>Here with a Contrite Heart you muſt declare the Sins you know, or ſuſpect to be Mortal, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (in that Courſe and Order you ranked them at your Examination, for the help of your Memory): Expreſſing exactly, or as near as you can, <hi>how often</hi> you have faln into each Sin; whether it concern'd a light <hi>Matter,</hi> or a <hi>Matter</hi> of Moment; whether you committed it with <hi>Foreſight,</hi> or <hi>Reflection;</hi> whether you ſtay'd in it long, or only a ſhort <hi>time;</hi> and, in Sins of Thought, tell whether you gave full <hi>Conſent</hi> thereto, or <hi>Delighted</hi> in it, or were only <hi>Negligent</hi> in rejecting it.</p>
               <p>But theſe, and ſuch like, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Circumſtances, you muſt unfold in as decent and few Words as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, relating what you are ſure of, as certain; what you doubt of, as doubtful; without any Mixture of Impertinent Stories concerning Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45075:18"/>Affairs, as Loſſes, Troubles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without Self-Commendations, and blaming, or even naming of others, without Concealing, or Excuſing your Sins, either thro' Fear or Shame; becauſe, <hi>He that hides his wicked Deeds, ſhall not be directed: But he that ſhall confeſs and ſhall forſake them, ſhall find Mercy,</hi> Prov. 28.13. See 1 Jo. 1.9.</p>
               <p>Hence, according to S. <hi>Aug. The Confeſſion of evil Works is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of good Works.</hi> Tract 12. in <hi>Jo.</hi> and more than that, <hi>Innocentiae proxima eſt humilis Confeſſio:</hi> An Humble Confeſſion brings the Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Perſon again (as near as poſſible) to the State of Innocency. Why then ſhould any one either fear or ſhame to do well, who neither fear'd nor ſham'd to do ill? Eſpecially being every Ghoſtly-Father is bound in Conſcience to conceal, and no way diſcloſe his Spiritual-Child's Failings, and to think better, and not worſe of him, for confeſſing his Sins.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:45075:19"/>
               <p>Having thus declar'd in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar your more grievous Offences, you may in general Terms, confeſs your leſſer Failings. Overſights, and Negligences, and then conclude, ſaying: <hi>For theſe my Since and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and for whatever elſe I cannot now call to mind, I am hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſorry, and purpoſe Amendment, humbly craving Pardon of God, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Abſolution of you, my Ghoſtly Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore I beſeech the B. Virgin</hi> Mary,—<hi>all the Saints in Heaven, and you, Father, to pray to God for me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ereatur, &amp;c.</hi> and to <hi>Indulgentiam, &amp;c.</hi> anſwer <hi>Amen,</hi> with Hearty Deſires, and Stedfaſt Hopes of Mercy and Pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III. <hi>Of</hi> Satisfaction.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Open your Ears and Heart to receive ſuch Reprehenſions and Directions, as ſhall be given you: And, if the Phyſician of your Soul <hi>opens your Iniquity to provoke you to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45075:19"/>Penance,</hi> 
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Lam. 2.14.</note>. eſteem it a Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and be thankful: <hi>For it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be rebuked of a wiſe Man, than to be deceived with the Flattery of Fools <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Eccleſ. 7.6.</note>: And better are the Wounds of him that loves, than the deceitful Kiſſes of him that hates</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Prov. 27.6.</note>. Hence, <hi>A Man that is prudent, and has diſcipline, will not murmur, when rebuked</hi> 
                  <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Ecclus. 10.28.</note>; but will ſhew himſelf Penitent: And, <hi>O, how good a thing it is, being rebuked, to ſhew Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: For ſo thou ſhalt avoid wilful Sin</hi> 
                  <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Ecclus. 20.4.</note>. On the contrary, <hi>A</hi> [per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly] <hi>ſinful Man will flee Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and according to his Will, will find an Excuſe</hi> 
                  <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Ecclus. 32.21.</note>, [for his Sins]. But <hi>he that rejects Diſcipline, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſes his Soul,</hi> Prov. 15.32.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Accept willingly the Penance enjoin'd, without eſteeming a hard one Burdenſome, or an eaſie one Contemptible: Becauſe no Penance (given now-a-days for many Mortal
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45075:20"/>Sins) is ſo hard, as what the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Canons of the Church aſſign'd to one only Crime, and yet the Severity of former Penances fall infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely ſhort of the Puniſiment due to Sin, in the Rigor of Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and is infinitely leſs than what your Iniquities deſerve. Again, no Penance eaſier than giving a Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or a Cup of Water; and yet ſo ſmall a Charity duly perform'd, is very acceptable to God, as you may ſee, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.42, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 41.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whilſt the Prieſt pronounces the Words of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſolution, ſaying, <hi>Ego te abſolvo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I abſolve thee in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> Beſeech Chriſt Jeſus to make good his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Promiſe of looſing in Heaven what his Miniſter looſes on Earth <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.19.</note>, and imagin your merciful Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſays to you, <hi>Thy Sins are forgiven thee—Go in Peace—and now ſin no more, leſt ſome worſe thing chance to thee.</hi> Luk. 7.48, 50. Jo. 8.11. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:45075:20"/>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">Pſ. 31.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe Iniquities are forgiven,</hi> as yours are; unleſs you have been wanting to the Grace of God, offer'd you in this Sacrament. Therefore give Thanks to God for his Mercy towards you, in ſo great a Bleſſing; and for that end ſay the <hi>Prayers after Confeſſion,</hi> as in the <hi>Manual</hi> or <hi>Primer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Fulfil carefully, and in due time, the Penance enjoin'd, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great or ſmall: <hi>For if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet had ſaid a great thing to thee,</hi> [or had the Prieſt enjoin'd a great Penance] <hi>ſurely thou ſhould'ſt have done it: How much more, whereas now he ſaid to thee, Be waſhed</hi> [or do a ſmall Penance] <hi>and thou ſhalt be clean</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Kings 4.5, 13.</note>. But if an eaſie Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance be impoſed for grievous Sins, then the ſupplying of its Inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency by voluntary Mortifications is left to your Zeal. <hi>Be zealous there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and do Penance <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Apoc. 3.19.</note>. Yeild Fruit, worthy of Penance <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Mat. 3.8.</note>. For
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45075:21"/>if we did judge</hi> [i. e. puniſh.] <hi>our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged</hi> 
                  <note n="(d)" place="bottom">1 Cor. 11.31.</note>, [i. e. puniſhed] by Almighty God. <hi>But if we do not Penance we ſhall fall into the Hands of our Lord <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Ecclus. 2.22.</note>: And it is horrible to fall into the Hands of the living God.</hi> Heb. 10.31.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, we muſt not repine at ſuch Afflictions and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as God ſends us in this Life, how great ſoever; but embrace them willingly, and bear them pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, in farther Satisfaction for our Sins; hoping that <hi>of our Lord we are chaſtiſed</hi> [Temporally], <hi>that with this World we be not damned</hi> [Eternally]. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.2, 5, 6. <hi>Judith</hi> 8.26, 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Walk warily, and take heed, leſt you fall again into your former Sins: For <hi>if a Man, that faſts in</hi> [Expiation of] <hi>his Sins, does the ſame again, what profits he in bumbling himſelf</hi> 
                  <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Ecclus 34.31.</note>? In caſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45075:21"/>of a Relapſe, one's State is much worſe than it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Prov. 26.11. Mat. 12.43. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Pet. 2.20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>. Therefore, to ſecure your ſelf from relapſing, you muſt <hi>cut off,</hi> and <hi>caſt away</hi> from you all dangerous <hi>Occaſions of Sin;</hi> how Pleaſing or Profitable ſoever to corrupt Nature. <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 25.36. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.8, 9.</p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> That you may know when and how often you are bound to have Recourſe to the Tribunal of Penance, take notice, that the Church obliges (under pain of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication) all and every one of the Faithful (after they are come to Years of Diſcretion) to Confeſs all their Mortal Sins faithfully to their own Prieſt (or Paſtor) at leaſt once a Year, and to perform carefully the Penance enjoin'd them: And this ſhe commands, to prevent the farther delaying the Converſion and and Reconciliation of Sinners to God.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:45075:22"/>
               <p>But, if you conſider ſeriouſly the Danger of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>from Day to Day</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ecclus 5.8, 9.</note>, and much more, <hi>from Year to Year,</hi> you will not ſlack to be converted to our Lord: But (on the contrary) as ſoon as you fall into Deadly Sin, you'll make ſure forthwith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent Sincerely, and to confeſs it at your firſt Opportunity, leſt in courſe of time you ſhould forget it, and ſo, at laſt, Die without Confeſſion, to the great Hazard of your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of</hi> Indulgences.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Whatſoever thou <hi>[Peter]</hi> ſhalt looſe in Earth, ſhall be looſed alſo in the Heavens,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 16.19.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>See alſo</hi>
                  <bibl>c. <hi>18.</hi> v. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>and</hi>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>2.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the Sacrament of Penance the Guilt of Sin is mercifully remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Eternal Pain due there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45075:22"/>is changeth into leſs or more Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Puniſhment according to the Meaſure of the Offence. Whence, <hi>To a great Wound</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Ambroſe) muſt be applied a great Plaiſter, and a great Satisfaction;</hi> which muſt be made to the utmoſt, (either in this, or the next Life) unleſs it be relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or abated by the Benefit of <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences:</hi> For gaining of which,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You muſt have true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, conſiſting of Hearty Sorrow for all your Sins, and a firm Purpoſe of Amendment. See Chap. 3. § 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You muſt perform with due Zeal all the Pious Works enjoin'd you, (that is, you muſt Faſt, Pray, give Alms, viſit Churches, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, Communicate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) according to the Intention of the Giver, and the Tenor of the Grant of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence;</hi> which commonly allows choice of Two, Three, or more things to be done, as every one's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, Ability, Opportunity, and other Circumſtances, require.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:45075:23"/>
            <p n="3">3. You muſt do the laſt part (at leaſt) of the ſaid Works in the State of Grace; that being a Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, without which, no <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> can be gain'd.</p>
            <p>And tho' Faith aſſures us, <note place="margin">Conc. Trid Seſſ. 25. c. 21.</note> 
               <hi>That the Power of granting Indulgences was given and left to the Paſtors of the Church by Jeſus Chriſt; and that the uſe of them is wholſome and beneficial to Chriſtians;</hi> yet, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this general Warrant, any particular Indulgence may be Invalid and Unbeneficial, either for want of Authority in the Giver, or thro' Deficiency in the Cauſe, or by reaſon of Indiſpoſition of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver: And therefore <hi>all well-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed Chriſtians</hi> (ſays <hi>Bellarmin) ſo accept of Papal</hi> [and Epiſcopal] <hi>Indulgences, as beſides them, to be careful to perform Works worthy of Penance, and to make Satisfaction for their Sins,</hi> by voluntary Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and patient Sufferings: As aforeſaid, Ch. III. § III. N. 5.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:45075:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of</hi> H. Communion.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Take ye, and eat: This is my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 26.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>GReat and diligent Care is to be had, in uſing all the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Catholick Church, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly and Holily, but moſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in receiving the moſt H. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Euchariſt; than which, the Church of God has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more worthy, nothing more Sacred and Admirable; becauſe in it is contain'd the principal and greateſt Gift of God, and the very Fountain and Author of all Grace and Holineſs, to wit, Chriſt our Lord. Therefore <hi>be thou</hi> [O Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian] <hi>prepar'd to meet thy God: For the Work is great; neither is an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation</hi> [to be] <hi>prepar'd for Man, but for God,</hi> Amos 4.12. 1 Par. 29.1.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:45075:24"/>
               <head>§ I. <hi>Before</hi> Communion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Ponder well the Immenſe Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt Receiving Worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (or Holily) and Unworthily, (or in the State of Mortal Sin).</p>
               <p>Of the former Chriſt ſays, <hi>My Fleſh is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink indeed. He that cats my Fleſh, and drinks my Blood, abides in me, and I in him: And he that eats me, the ſame ſhall live by me: He that eats,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>has Life Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and I will raiſe him up in the laſt Day, and he ſhall live for ever.</hi> John 6. From all which 'tis plain, that the Life of <hi>Grace</hi> here, and of <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter, is the happy Effect and Fruit of receiving Worthily.</p>
               <p>Of the latter S. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall eat the Bread, or drink the Chalice of our Lord unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, ſhall be guilty of the Body and Blood of our Lord.</hi> And again, <hi>He that eats and drinks unworthily, eats and drinks Judgment to himſelf. Therefore
[viz.</hi> for receiving Unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily] <hi>are there among you many weak
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45075:24"/>and feeble</hi> [in Body and Soul], <hi>and many ſleep [i. e.</hi> Die, both Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and Eternally]. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. O Diſmal <hi>Guilt, Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> of Unworthy Receiving!</p>
               <p>But why ſhould I wonder hereat, ſince the Blood of Chriſt cries to Heaven for Vengeance (like that of <hi>Abel</hi>) againſt every Unworthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant, <note place="margin">Gen. 4.10.</note> who <hi>Crucifying again to himſelf the Son of God, and making him a Mockery, has trodden the Son of God under Foot, and eſteem'd the Blood of the Teſtament polluted, wherein he is ſanctified?</hi> Heb. 6.6. c. 10. v. 29. Whereas on the contrary, <note place="margin">Heb. 12.24.</note> 
                  <hi>The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of the New-Teſtament, Jeſus, and the ſprinkling of his Blood, ſpeak better than</hi> Abel, and plead effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally both Mercy and Pardon, in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of worthy Communicants.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>You cannot be Partakers of the Table of our Lord, and of the Table of Devils
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">1 Cor. 10.21.</note>. For what Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has Juſtice with Iniquity? Or what Society is there between Light
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45075:25"/>and Darkneſs? And what Agreement with Chriſt and</hi> Belial
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">2 Cor. 6.14, 15.</note>? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, before Receiving, <hi>Purge away the old Leaven</hi> [of Mortal Sins and Affections thereto, by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Penance], <hi>that you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a new Paſte, and let us Feaſt</hi> [at the Table of our Lord]; <hi>not in the Leaven of Malice and Wickedneſs, but in the Azims of Sincerity and Truth</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="bottom">1 Cor. 5.7, 8.</note>. And, <hi>becauſe a little Leaven corrupts the whole Paſte</hi> 
                  <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Gal. 5.9.</note>, to be wholly Clean and Unleaven'd, you muſt purge your Souls likewiſe from Venial Sins, and from all Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to them, and to Worldly Vanities. This is what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle inſinuates, ſaying: <hi>Let a Man prove himſelf</hi> [by Examining and Rectifying his Conſcience], <hi>and ſo let him eat,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 11.28.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You muſt not only <hi>lay away the old Man, <note place="margin">Eph. 4.24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> who is corrupted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Deſires of Error, but you muſt alſo be renew'd in the Spirit of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45075:25"/>your Mind, and put on the new Man, who, according to God, is created in Juſtice and Holineſs of the Truth.</hi> That is, beſides the Cleanſing of your Soul from Sins and Sinful Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, you muſt Adorn it with Holy Thoughts, Affections, and Acts of Vertue. <hi>Put ye on therefore, <note place="margin">Col. 3.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> as the Elect of God, Holy and Beloved, the Bowels of Mercy, Benignity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Modeſty, Patience, ſupporting one another, and pardoning one another, if any one have a Quarrel againſt any Man; as our Lord pardon'd us, ſo you alſo. But above all theſe things, have Charity, which is the Band of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> &amp;c. Leſt, after your Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in being call'd to the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age-Supper of the Lamb, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo unfortunate, as to be caſt into utter Darkneſs, for coming without the Wedding-Garment of Charity, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.9. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence, that your Inward Man may be adorn'd in a manner ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Divine Gueſt you are to entertain, ſay the <hi>Prayers before Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:45075:26"/>as in the <hi>Manual</hi> or <hi>Primer,</hi> eliciting Acts of <hi>Faith, Hope, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Humility,</hi> and other Vertues, whilſt you ſay them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Beſides Purity and Piety of Soul, you muſt bring along with you to the Table of our Lord, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Body agreeable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; that is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt be Faſting, (ſo as not to have eat or drunk any thing) at leaſt from the Midnight before you Communicate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Married Perſons are advis'd <hi>by Mutual Conſent</hi> to practiſe Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency ſome Days and Nights before they come to Holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>that they may give themſelves to Prayer</hi> with more Freedom, from <hi>Tribulation of the Fleſh,</hi> and with leſs <hi>Impediment</hi> in the Service of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5, 28, 35. Such Continency being a Diſpoſition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd in thoſe that were to eat the Hallowed Bread of the Old Law; and much rather for them, that by eating the Euchariſtical Bread of the New Law, are to partake of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45075:26"/>Body of our Lord, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.3, 4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your Faces and Hands muſt be clean: Your Apparel Modeſt and Decent, and your whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment exact in every Point of Exterior Reverence: Of which hereafter, Ch. XII. § II. N. 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. II. <hi>At</hi> Communion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Kneel down on both Knees before the Altar, cover your Hands with the Towel, ſay the <hi>Confiteor</hi> to your ſelf, (along with the Clerk) deeply reſenting your Sins: To <hi>Miſereatur veſtri, &amp;c.</hi> and to <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam,</hi> &amp;c. anſwer <hi>Amen,</hi> with Deſires and Hopes of Pardon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whilſt the Prieſt holds up the B. Sacrament towards you, and ſays, <hi>Ecce Agnus Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Jo. 1.29.</note>, by a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Faith you muſt <hi>diſcern the Body of our Lord</hi> 
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">1 Cor. 11.29.</note>, under the outward Appearance of Bread; and doubt not to ſay in Heart, <hi>Behold He</hi> [whom my Soul loves] <hi>ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45075:27"/>our Wall, looking thro' the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, looking forth by the Grates,</hi> [or outward Symbols]. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whilſt the Prieſt repeats <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne non ſum Dignus,</hi> &amp;c. three ſeveral times, you muſt humbly adore Chriſt in the B. Sacrament, and (with a deep Senſe of own Unworthineſs, and of Chriſt's Powerful Mercy) ſay thrice in a low Voice,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, I am not worthy thou ſhould'ſt enter under my Roof; but only ſay the Word, and my</hi> [Soul] <hi>ſhall be healed;</hi> and of Unworthy, I ſhall be made Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When the B. Sacrament is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd you, (opening your Mouth conveniently, and your Heart affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately) receive it with Profound Reverence, in Remembrance of Chriſt's Paſſion and Death <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 22.19.</note>, and ſay, (not in Words, but in Thoughts), <hi>The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt keep my Soul to Life Everlaſting,</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:45075:27"/>
               <head>§ III. <hi>After</hi> Communion.</head>
               <p>Go not forthwith out of the Church, fall not into Diſcourſe with others, gaze not round about, ſpit not preſently, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but (baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Worldly Concerns quite out of your Mind) continue for a time in Ardent Prayer, and in Holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, <hi>Taſte, and ſee, <note place="margin">Pſ. 33.9.</note> that our Lord is ſweet;</hi> giving Thanks to God for ſo ſingular a Benefit, as alſo for our Lord's moſt Sacred Paſſion, in Memory whereof this Myſtery is and will be Celebrated and Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the World's end. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</p>
               <p>Hence, immediately after Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, in Tranſports of Comfort and Joy, you may ſay, <hi>I have found him whom my Soul loves,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Cant. 3.4.</note>. <hi>A bundle of Myrrh my Beloved to me, he ſhall abide between my Breaſts <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Cant. 1.13.</note>. I live, now not I, but Chriſt lives in me,</hi> Gal. 2.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Soul, bleſs thou our Lord, and all things that are within me, bleſs ye
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45075:28"/>his Holy Name. Bleſs our Lord</hi> [in ſupply of my Defects] <hi>all ye his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, mighty in Power, doing his Word, that fear the Voice of his Words. Bleſs our Lord, all ye his Hoſts, you his Miniſters, that do his Will. Bleſs ye our Lord, all his Works, in every Place of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> Pſ. 102.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>O Sacred Banquet! in which Chriſt is receiv'd, the Memory of his Paſſion is renew'd, our Soul is fill'd with Grace, and a Pledge of future Glory is given us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> Bread from Heaven thou haſt given us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Having in it all that is Delightful.</p>
                  <p>O God, who under this Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sacrament haſt left unto us the Memory of thy Paſſion; grant, we beſeech thee, that we may ſo worſhip the Sacred Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of thy Body and Blood, that we may continually feel in us the Fruit of thy Redemption, who liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and reigneſt, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:45075:28"/>
               <p>Whilſt the Prieſt gives the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, make the Sign of the Croſs upon your ſelf, and ſay, <hi>The Bleſſing of Almighty God, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, deſcend upon us, and remain always.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Then ſay the <hi>Prayers after Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as in the <hi>Manual</hi> or <hi>Primer:</hi> Becauſe to continue thus, after Communion, in Prayer and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, is to imitate Chriſt and his H. Apoſtles; <hi>who, an Hymn being ſaid, went forth.</hi> But to fail in this Duty, is to imitate the Accurſed <hi>Judas, who, having received, went preſently forth,</hi> to betray Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30. <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Take Care to ſpend the reſt of the Day Holily, according to the Rules ſet down, Chap. XXII.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:45075:29"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the</hi> Communion <hi>of the</hi> Sick.</head>
            <p>EVery time you Communicate, and eſpecially in Sickneſs, and in Danger of Death, you muſt have Acceſs to the Table of our Lord, in ſuch Diſpoſition of Soul, as if you were immediately to leave the World.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Infirm Perſons, and ſuch as are Sick of Lingring Diſtempers, (tho' they be not dangerouſly Ill) both may and ought to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate frequently, during their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition; that Vertue may be perfected in Infirmity, and the Soul (being ſtrengthned by H. Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) may better ſuſtain Bodily Weakneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe (no leſs than People in Health) muſt be <hi>Faſting,</hi> when they Receive, ſo as not to have taken any thing at all, either of Food or Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, beforehand.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:45075:29"/>
            <p>Likewiſe, <hi>Before, At,</hi> and <hi>After Communion,</hi> they muſt obſerve (as near as they can) the Directions gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Perſons in Health. Chap. V. throughout.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But when a Man is ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly Sick, that 'tis probable it will be the laſt time he ſhall be able to receive the B. Sacrament, then he may receive as his <hi>Viaticum,</hi> altho' he be not Faſting; and (with all poſſible Care and Diligence) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is to be made in due time, leſt ſuch an one ſhould Die deprived of ſo great a Good, either thro' his own Inadvertency, or the Neglect of his Tenders.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Before the Prieſt comes to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter Communion to the Sick, his Chamber muſt be made clean, and in it a Table muſt be cover'd with a clean Linnen Cloth, on which the B. Sacrament may be decently placed: <hi>H. Water,</hi> and <hi>Hallowed Candles, Wine,</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> muſt likewiſe be prepar'd: Beſides, a clean Linnen Cloth muſt be laid
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45075:30"/>before the Breaſt of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant, and other Ornaments of the Room, muſt be added, according to each one's Ability.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Receiving the</hi> H. Euchariſt, <hi>as your</hi> Viaticum.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Ariſe, eat, for thou haſt yet a great Way to go. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>3 Kin. 9.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AFter the Sick Man has uſed his utmoſt Endeavours to ſupply the Defects of his former particular Confeſſions, by a general Confeſſion of all, or at leaſt of the moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sins of his whole Life, and has perform'd the Duties of Penance with that Sincerity and Exactneſs, which is requiſite for a Dying Perſon, then his Charitable Aſſiſtant may diſpoſe him for his <hi>Viaticum,</hi> by reading unto him this following Exhortation.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:45075:30"/>
               <head>§ I. <hi>Before Receiving.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Beloved Brother [or Siſter], the <hi>H. Euchariſt</hi> is our <hi>Viaticum,</hi> or Voyage-Food, given us from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, (as <hi>Manna</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ex. 16.13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>) for our Spiritual Support and Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, during our Pilgrimage on Earth, that we may not fail nor faint in our way, but may paſs ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully thro' the Wilderneſs of this Life, and the Straits of Sickneſs and Death, unto the Region of Bliſs. <note place="margin">Wiſd. 16.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>And as Manna had in it all Delightfulneſs, and the Sweetneſs of all Taſte; and, ſerving every Man's Will, was turn'd to that, which every Man deſired;</hi> ſo (and much more) the <hi>H. Euchariſt</hi> contains and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to its worthy Receiver all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Contentment, and fills the Soul of every-one with Graces ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Condition and Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>John</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>On this Truth S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is moſt Divinely Eloquent, ſaying;
<q>Our Lord in the Euchariſt is to us all in all. If you will heal your
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45075:31"/>Wounds, he is the Medicine; if you be Thirſty, he is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; if you be loaden with Sins, he is Juſtice; if you ſtand in need of Aſſiſtance, he is Power; if you fear Death, he is Life; if you will go to Heaven, he is the Way; if you fly Darkneſs, he is the Light; if you be Hungry, he is Food.</q> Taſte then, and ſee, how ſweet our Lord is: And looking upon this Communion, as your laſt, recollect your Thoughts, and ſummon all the Affections of your Soul, to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your Lord ſo, that the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this may ſupply all the Defects of your former Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and let your Intention be to Communicate, that ſo you may be enabled to finiſh happily the great Journey (which now you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring upon) between Earth and Heaven.</p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> 
                  <hi>Read here to the Sick Party the Prayers before Receiving, as in the Manual or Primer; and after them what follows.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:45075:31"/>
               <head>§ II. <hi>At Receiving.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. As ſoon as the B. Sacrament enters your Chamber, you muſt raiſe up your ſelf as you are able, and (either on your Knees, or with Humble Bowing of your Head) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore your Lord and Saviour, and with joyful Aſtoniſhment, ſay to him; <hi>What is Man, that thou art mindful of him? Or the Son of Man, that thou viſiteſt him <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Pſ. 8.5.</note>? Whence is this to me, that—my Lord comes to me</hi> 
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Luk. 1.43.</note>?</p>
               <p n="2">2. With a Contrite Heart ſay (or hear) the <hi>Confiteor,</hi> and receive the Prieſt's Abſolution and Bleſſing, with a fervent Deſire of the Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your Sins, and Hopes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtored to the Grace and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When the Prieſt holds up the B. Sacrament towards you, ſaying, <hi>Ecce Agnus Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold the Lamb of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.29. Humble your ſelf in the Preſence of Chriſt, and ſay
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45075:32"/>in Heart; <hi>To the Lamb that was ſlain, be Bleſſing, and Honour, and Power, for ever and ever,</hi> Apoc. 5.12, 13.</p>
               <p>At the Repetition of <hi>Domine, non ſum Dignus,</hi> &amp;c. acknowledge your great Unworthineſs, and beſeech our Lord to make you Worthy of him, ſaying; <hi>Lord, I am not Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> &amp;c. But, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before, Chap. V. § II. Num. 3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. With great Reverence and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion open your Mouth and Heart to receive the Bread of Life, and at the ſame time ſay in Spirit; <hi>The</hi> Viaticum <hi>of the Body of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, keep me from my Ghoſtly E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and bring me to Life Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III. <hi>After Receiving.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Deſire the Sick Perſon to let his Thoughts and Affections accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany your Words, and then read what follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have found,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>My Soul bleſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O Sacred Banquet,</hi> &amp;c. as before, Chap. V. § III.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:45075:32"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Almighty and merciful God, vouchſafe (I beſeech thee) to ſtrengthen me (thy Unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant) with thy Grace, by vertue of this Sacrament, that in the Hour of my Death the Enemy may not prevail againſt me, but with thy Angels I may have a happy Paſſage to Eternal Life, thro' Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt prepared in my Sight a Table againſt them that trouble me</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Pſ. 22.5.</note>. O grant, for thy Mercy ſake, that I may <hi>walk in the Strength of this Food unto the Mount of God <note n="(b)" place="bottom">3 Kin. 19.8.</note>, where I ſhall not Hunger nor Thirſt any more,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.16.</note>, <hi>but ſhall be Inebriated with the Plenty of thy Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Pſ. 35.9.</note>, <hi>and ſhall have the Happineſs to ſit in the Beauty of Peace, and in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of Confidence, and in wealthy Reſt</hi> 
                  <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Iſa. 32.18.</note>, for all Eternity.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:45075:33"/>
               <p>After this, you may either leave the Sick Man to his own Thoughts, or go on with reading the <hi>Prayers after Receiving,</hi> as in the <hi>Manual,</hi> or <hi>Primer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>How often the</hi> H. Euchariſt <hi>is to be received Really, and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SUch is the neceſſity of H. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, that <hi>unleſs you eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, you ſhall not have Life in you,</hi> Jo. 6.53.</p>
            <p>Hence the Church commands (under pain of Excommunication) all and every one of the Faithful (after they come to Years of Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and can ſufficiently diſcern the Body of our Lord from ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Food) to receive the H. Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> Reverently, at leaſt once every Year, and that at <hi>Eaſter,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:45075:33"/>intending by this Decree to prevent farther delaying a Duty, on which the Soul's Spiritual Life ſo abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depends.</p>
            <p>And beſides which Precept, the Church Counſels and Admoniſhes ſuch as are capable of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reliſhing this Sacrament, to receive the ſame holily and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, eſpecially on the more Solemn Feaſts of the Year; that by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they may not only Preſerve, but alſo Improve and Augment Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Life and Health.</p>
            <p>And tho' Chriſt in the Text above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited mentions Communion in <hi>both Kinds,</hi> yet both before and after it he attributes all that can be deſired, to Communion, in <hi>one Kind,</hi> ſaying; <hi>He that eats this Bread, ſhall live for ever,</hi> Jo. 6.51, 58. Conſequently, as a thing indifferent, 'tis left to the Church, to determine the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it either way, according to Diſcretion. See <hi>Luke</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 30, 31, 35. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.42. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 7, 11.</p>
            <p>Beſides Communicating Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally and Really at the Times
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45075:34"/>aforeſaid, there is a way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating Spiritually, and in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, by uniting your Heart to the quickning Fleſh of our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our with Ardent Affections, and Acts of Faith, Hope, and Charity, relating to Chriſt, as preſent in the H. Euchariſt. And it is to be uſed of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> when one ſhould receive Sacramentally, but cannot, either thro' Indiſpoſition, or for want of Opportunity: In which Caſes God Almighty requires and accepts of the Will for the Work. It may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be uſed at <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> and with much Profit, as often as you hear <hi>Maſs,</hi> and are preſent, when others Communicate really, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> For farther Directions, with Prayers, both before and after <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Communion,</hi> and <hi>Confirmation,</hi> I refer you to a Treatiſe, entitled, <hi>Inſtructions for Confeſſion and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:45075:34"/>
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of</hi> Extreme Unction. <hi>To be read to the Sick, after he has received his</hi> Viaticum.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Is any Man ſick amongſt you? Let him bring in the Prieſts of the Church, and let them Pray over him, Anointing him with Oyl in the Name of our Lord: And the Prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the ſick Man, and our Lord will raiſe him up; and if he be in Sins, they ſhall be forgiven him. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>James 5.13.</hi> &amp;c.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE H. Sacrament of <hi>Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> (thus recommended by S. <hi>James</hi>) was Inſtituted by Chriſt our Lord <note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 6.13.</note>, as an Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Medicin, wholſom both for the Bodies and Souls of Sick Perſons: <hi>For their Bodies;</hi> in that, by its Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Vertue and Efficacy, it procures and reſtores Corporal <hi>Health,</hi> when 'tis Profitable and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45075:35"/>Advantageous to the Soul. <hi>For their Souls;</hi> in that it gives <hi>Grace,</hi> which remits Venial Sins, frees the Soul from Diſorderly Affections, and all other Relicks of Mortal Sins, ſtrengthens the Spirit with Divine Hope, Comfort, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, againſt the Inordinate Fears of Death and Judgment, againſt Deſpair of God's Mercy, againſt the laſt and moſt violent Aſſaults of our Ghoſtly Enemy, and in fine, makes Sickneſs and Death it ſelf far more eaſie and welcome, than otherwiſe they could be to Fleſh and Blood.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (as you deſire your Soul's Welfare in its laſt and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Extremities) neglect not this Sacrament, but take the Apoſtle's Advice, in ſending for the Miniſter of it, whilſt your Underſtanding and Senſes are perfect; that by Actual Faith and Devotion you may contribute to a more plentiful Receiving of its Grace and happy Effects. For attaining which,</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:45075:35"/>
               <head>§ I. <hi>Before</hi> Extreme Unction.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The things hereafter ſet down, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prepared.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In regard the Prieſt ordinarily repeats the Seven Penitential Pſalms as he goes to Anoil the Sick, it is meet that you join with him in the ſame Devotion, and cauſe them to be read to you; deſiring all preſent to Pray with and for you, that you may receive this Sacrament Worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that this Divine Medicin may work a perfect Cure upon your Soul, whatever befalls your Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. When the Prieſt enters your Chamber to Anoil you, think your ſelf to be the Diſtreſs'd Traveller that fell among Thieves, who ſpoiled, wounded, and left him half dead; ſuch being the State of every Sinner; and eſteem the Prieſt to be the good <hi>Samaritan;</hi> who, ſeeing him ſo abuſed, was moved with Mercy, and going unto him, bound up his Wounds, pouring in Oyl, <hi>&amp;c. Luke</hi> 10.30. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:45075:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:45075:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:45075:37"/>
               <p n="3">3. When he offers you the Croſs, ſalute it devoutly, in Teſtimony of your Faith, Hope, and Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt Crucified, and ſay, <hi>I believe the Son of God ſuffer'd upon the Croſs to ſave me: I hope he will apply the Merits of his Paſſion to my Soul, in vertue of this Sacrament: And for the Love of him that died for me, I am truly content to die, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now, of this very Sickneſs, or when and after what manner elſe he pleaſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. When he ſprinkles you and the By-ſtanders with H. Water, ſay to God; <hi>Thou ſhalt ſprinkle,</hi> &amp;c. Attend (as much as you are able) to what he ſays (for your Comfort and Encouragement) concerning the Vertue and Efficacy of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which helps the Sick, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Recover, or Die well, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as God determines its Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Good of the Receiver, and take Courage, whilſt he puts you in Hopes of Eternal Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:45075:37"/>
               <head>§ II. <hi>At</hi> Extreme Unction.</head>
               <p>Say [or Hear] the <hi>Confiteor</hi> [either in Latin or Engliſh] with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite Heart. To <hi>Miſereatur,</hi> &amp;c. and to <hi>Indulgentiam,</hi> &amp;c. anſwer <hi>Amen,</hi> with Deſires and Hopes of Pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whilſt the Prieſt Anoils,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Your Eyes,</item>
                     <item>2. Your Ears,</item>
                     <item>3. Your Noſtrils,</item>
                     <item>4. Your Mouth,</item>
                     <item>5. Your Hands,</item>
                     <item>6. Your Feet,</item>
                     <item>7. Your Reins,</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſeech Almighty God, for his tender Mercies ſake, to forgive, by this H. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, whatſoever you have ſinned</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By Seeing.</item>
                     <item>2. By Hearing.</item>
                     <item>3. By Smelling.</item>
                     <item>4. By Taſting and Speaking.</item>
                     <item>5. By Touching.</item>
                     <item>6. By Going Ill Ways.</item>
                     <item>7. By Luſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III. <hi>After</hi> Extreme Unction.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Join in Prayer with the Prieſt, and queſtion not, but God hears thoſe Solemn and Holy Addreſſes, which he makes for you, in the Perſon of Chriſt, and his Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Give Thanks to God for his Goodneſs and Mercy towards us in the Sacraments you have received: Many Thouſands in the World lye
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45075:38"/>now a Dying, without the Helps to Die well, which you have had in ſo full a meaſure, that nothing is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards making you happy with Grace here, and with Glory hereafter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Keep in mind the wholeſom Admonitions given you by the Prieſt, to the end you may thereby drive away the Devil's Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons couragiouſly, and Die in our Lord comfortably; than which no greater Bleſſing can befal you on this ſide Heaven, <hi>&amp;c. Apoc.</hi> 14.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Have always by you H. Water and a Crucifix, that you may often Uſe the firſt, and frequently Behold, Kiſs, and Embrace the latter, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your Devotion; and in ſo doing ſay to your Dear Redeemer;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>O good Jeſu, hear me; within thy Wounds hide me; ſuffer me not to be ſeparated from thee; from the Malignant Enemy defend me; at the Hour of my Death call me, and bid me come to thee, that with thy Saints I may praiſe thee, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:45075:38"/>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Before the Prieſt comes to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noil a Sick Perſon, there muſt be prepar'd H. Water, and a Table, (cover'd with a White Linnen Cloth having upon it a <hi>Crucifix,</hi> with two <hi>Hallowed Candles</hi>) on which the H. Oyls are to be placed at his Entrance into the Room: A little Platter, with <hi>Cotton,</hi> [or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like] ſhared into Six or Seven little Parcels, to wipe off the Oyl from the Parts Anointed: <hi>Crumbs of Bread</hi> to Cleanſe, and <hi>Water</hi> to Waſh his Hands: A <hi>Wax-Candle,</hi> to give him Light (if need be) whilſt he Anoils; and Care muſt be taken, that all things be Clean and Decent about the Sick.</p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Beſides the real Receiving of our <hi>Viaticum</hi> and <hi>Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> in the time of Sickneſs, there is a very Profitable Way of Receiving them Spiritually in the time of Health; which conſiſts in Reading. Meditating, and Practiſing what has been ſaid of theſe two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, once a Month, while you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45075:39"/>live; that you may be the better prepar'd for doing theſe Duties well, when you come to Die. For farther Inſtructions in this Point, I refer you to the <hi>Chriſtian Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> to <hi>The Daily Exerciſes of a Chriſtian Life,</hi> and to <hi>The Manual of the Poor Man's Devotion:</hi> At the end of which Books, you may find this Exerciſe amply ſet forth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of</hi> Holy Orders.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Every High <hi>[and Inferior]</hi> Prieſt, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from among Men, is appointed for Men in thoſe things, that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 5.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> &amp;c. See
<bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 13.2, 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HOly Orders concern the Laity no farther than,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To know and believe Them to be a Sacrament of the Goſpel; in which the Perſons Ordain'd by
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45075:39"/>Impoſition of Hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are made Miniſters of Chriſt, and Diſpenſers of the Myſteries of God, and do thence receive Special Grace for ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the Miniſtry aſſign'd them. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5, 6. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3, 4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To know and believe, that as it is the Duty of Paſtors to <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Feed</hi> their Flocks Spiritually <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Acts 20.28. 1 Pet. 5.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>; ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their Flocks to <hi>Honour <note n="(b)" place="bottom">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Obey</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Heb. 13.17.</note>, and <hi>Feed</hi> their Paſtors Corporally <note n="(d)" place="bottom">1 Cor. 9.7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>; that neither Contempt nor Indigency may be a Hindrance to the due Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their Function <note n="(e)" place="bottom">2 Tim. 2.3, 4.</note>.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> 
               <hi>Note</hi> here, that at Four ſeveral times in the Year, call'd <hi>Ember-Days,</hi> our Biſhops Adminiſter this Sacrament, Ordaining Prieſts and Deacons, and other Miniſters of the Church, with Prayer and Faſting, after the Example of Chriſt and his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45075:40"/>Apoſtles, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.12, 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2, 3. And becauſe it highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Laity to be provided with good Paſtors, you muſt not fail <hi>on thoſe Days</hi> to Faſt, and <hi>Pray the Lord of the Harveſt, that he ſend forth Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
[not Loiterers <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 20.6.</note>] <hi>into his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt;</hi> and that they may rightly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe <hi>the Power, which our Lord has given</hi> them, <hi>unto Edification; and not unto Deſtruction.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 38. 2 Cor. 13.10.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP XI. <hi>Of</hi> Matrimony.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>This is a great Sacrament in Chriſt, and in the Church. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eph. 5.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MAtrimony is an inſeparable Conjunction (or, Joining together) of a Man and a Woman for the end of Wedlock, ordain'd and made by God himſelf, <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 2.22.24. Mat. 19.6.</note> Sanctified by Chriſt, and made a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45075:40"/>great <hi>Sacrament</hi> [repreſenting and reſembling the Spiritual Union be-Chriſt and his Church]: Which gives Special <hi>Grace</hi> to Man and Wife, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bling them to diſcharge Holily their reſpective <hi>Duties</hi> towards one another, and towards their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. See Chap. XXVII.</p>
            <p>For Receiving and Retaining of which Matrimonial Grace, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſpoſitions are neceſſary.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§ I. <hi>Before</hi> Marriage.</head>
               <p n="1">1. A good Intention is required; which conſiſts in Deſiring and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to Marry for one or more of the ends for which God Ordain'd, and Chriſt Sanctified Wedlock: As,</p>
               <p>Firſt, and Principally, for the love of Children and Poſterity, in which the Name of God may be Bleſſed for ever. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27, 28. <hi>Tob.</hi> 6.22. <hi>ch.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For the ſake of mutual Society, and Aſſiſtance of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:45075:41"/>
               <p>Thirdly, For a remedy againſt Concupiſcence, and Sins of the Fleſh. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2.8.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A good Intention muſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, and carried on with Vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s Converſation, and Modeſt Beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our (throughout the whole S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es of Courtſhip) as the beſt means to Succeed in the Choice of a good Wife or Husband: For <hi>Houſe and Riches are the Gifts of Parents; but of our Lord properly, a good Wife <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Prov. 19.14.</note>. A good Woman is a good Portion; in the good Portion of them that fear God, ſhall ſhe be given to a Man for good Deeds</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Ecclus 26.3.</note>. Thus <hi>Sara</hi> was reſerved and given to <hi>Tobie,</hi> as the Angel declared to <hi>Raguel,</hi> her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaying, <hi>Fear not to give her to this Man; for to him, fearing God, is thy Daughter due to be his Wife, therefore another could not have her. Tob.</hi> 7.12. See <hi>Ecclus</hi> 7.27.</p>
               <p>Hence, in the time of Courtſhip, all Pretenders to Marriage, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Women, muſt imitate <hi>Sara</hi>'s
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45075:41"/>Conduct; who Appeals to God, as Witneſs of her Modeſty and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, ſaying, <hi>Thou knoweſt, Lord, that I never Coveted a Husband, and have kept my Soul clean from all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence; never have I companied my ſelf with Sporters; neither have I made my ſelf partaker with them, that walk in Lightneſs; but a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band I Conſented to take, with thy Fear, not with my Luſt.</hi> Tob. 3.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A little before Marriage, the Parties (having prepared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diligently before-hand) muſt go to Confeſſion, in order to put their Souls in the State of Grace, neceſſary for Receiving Worthily the Holy Sacrament of Matrimony; and they would do well to Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate either before or after Marriage, according as occaſion beſt Serves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§ II. <hi>At</hi> Marriage.</head>
               <p>Not only the State of Grace, but alſo Interior Devotion, and Exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Decency and Reverence are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; becauſe Matrimony is a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45075:42"/>thing, and ought to be treated Holily (by the Parties themſelves) and reſpectfully (by all preſent thereat). And as true Deuotion, and pious Deſires of thoſe concern'd in the Marriage at <hi>Cana,</hi> were the principal Invitations, that moved <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> to honour it with their Preſence, and induced Her to repreſent Affectionately, and Him to ſupply Miraculouſly their want of Wine. <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, true Devotion and due Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, are the beſt Means you can uſe for obtaining of the Mother and Son of God, Spiritual Bleſſings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Nuptials.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III. <hi>After</hi> Marriage.</head>
               <p>According to the direction of the Angel <hi>Raphael,</hi> and the Example of <hi>Tobie</hi> and <hi>Sara,</hi> the new Married Couple are adviſed to be Continent for Three Days and Nights, and give themſelves (that while) to Prayer, that God may give a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to them in the State of Life, they have undertaken: This done,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45075:42"/>and the Prieſt's Benediction being receiv'd, after Maſs ſaid for them, they may Conſummate their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, not like Brutes or Heathens, but with the fear of our Lord; and with the fear of our Lord muſt they likewiſe Celebrate the Marriage-Feaſt. <hi>Tob.</hi> 6.17, <hi>&amp;c. c.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3, <hi>&amp;c. Tob.</hi> 9.12.</p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Note here, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Parents muſt not Match their Children a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Wills, nor Children Marry contrary to the Rational Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of their Parents. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.57. <hi>c.</hi> 26. <hi>v.</hi> 34, 35.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits the pompous Solemnities of Marriage in <hi>Advent</hi> and <hi>Lent,</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable Entertainments at thoſe Times of Publick Mourning and Penance: For <hi>Muſick in Mourning is a Tale out of Time: But Scourges and Doctrin are at all Times</hi> [and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in <hi>Advent</hi> and <hi>Lent] Wiſdom, Ecclus</hi> 22.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the want of due Preparations and Diſpoſitions afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45075:43"/>is the occaſion, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny now-a-days are ſo unfortunate and miſerable in the State of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That they do well, who keep the Anniverſary-Day of their Marriage; by reflecting then, How they have complied with the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of their State; by Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for, and Reſolving to Amend what has been Amiſs; by craving Grace for better Management of their Vocation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of</hi> Churching Women <hi>after</hi> Child birth.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>I make others to bring forth Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſays the Lord. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 66.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>'TIS a Pious and Laudable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in the Church, for Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, after Child-birth, to come to Church, and give God
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45075:43"/>Thanks for their ſafe Delivery, and receive the Prieſt's Benediction: In compliance to which Cuſtom, the Child-bed Woman muſt do what follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whilſt ſhe kneels at the Church-Door with a lighted Candle in her Hand, and the Prieſt reads over her the XXIII. Pſalm, let her <hi>Reflect,</hi> and call to mind, How the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> at the Month-end after her Delivery, carried her little Son Jeſus into <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to preſent him (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſelf) to our Lord. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.22. And let her <hi>Pray,</hi> that what ſhe now does in imitation of our Lady, may find acceptance in the ſight of God, thro' Chriſt our Saviour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whilſt the Prieſt Conducts her into the Church, ſaying, <hi>Enter into the Temple of God: Adore the Son of the Bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>who has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee fruitfulneſs of Off-ſpring;</hi> let her piouſly <hi>Reſolve</hi> to do what he requires, and let her <hi>ſay in Heart</hi> to God, <hi>In the multitude of thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I will Enter into thy Houſe: I
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45075:44"/>will Adore towards thy Holy</hi> Altar <hi>in thy Fear: Lord, Conduct me in thy Juſtice.</hi> Pſal. 5.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whilſt ſhe kneels before the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, let her <hi>Give thanks</hi> to God for the Bleſſings and Benefits he has beſtow'd upon her, and her Child: Let her <hi>Offer</hi> her ſelf, and her little one, to the Father of Mercies; and let her <hi>Pray</hi> Devoutly with the Prieſt, for a Continuation, and a Holy Uſe of God's Gifts and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, during Life; that, after Death, ſhe, with her Child, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y come to Everlaſting Bliſs, thro' the Merits of Chriſt, and the Interceſſion of his Bleſſed Mother.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Whilſt the Prieſt gives the Benediction, ſaying, <hi>The Peace and Bleſſing of Almighty God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, deſcend upon thee, and remain always;</hi> let her Earneſt Wiſhes go along with his Prayer, and let her Seal them up with a hearty <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:45075:44"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of</hi> Prayer.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>You have not; <hi>either</hi> becauſe you ask not, <hi>or</hi> becauſe you ask amiſs. Ask <hi>therefore rightly,</hi> and it ſhall be given you. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jam. 4.2, 3. Mat. 7.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§ I. <hi>Before</hi> Prayer. <note place="margin">Ecclus 18.</note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prepare thy Soul; and be not as a Man that tempts God.</hi> That is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Think ſeriouſly what you are going to do: For <hi>You</hi> are about to treat with <hi>God</hi> concerning the only neceſſary Affair of your Salvation, <hi>&amp;c. Duſt, and Aſhes</hi> are about to Speak and Converſe with the <hi>Lord of Heaven and Earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Setting aſide all other Buſineſs, chuſe ſuch Time and Place, as are moſt free from Noiſe and Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and <hi>that may give you power, without impediment, to attend upon our Lord.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.35.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:45075:45"/>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider your ſelf in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, who does not hear Sinners, until they Repent. <hi>Jo.</hi> 9.31. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.1, &amp;c. <note n="*" place="margin">Ecclus 12.3.</note> Therefore, in caſe you are Guilty of Morral Sin, endeavour to put your ſelf in the State of Grace by an Act of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My God, I am confounded and aſhamed to lift up my Face to thee: becauſe my Iniquities are multiplied—and I have ſinned grievouſly unto this Day. Nevertheleſs</hi> (in regard thy Mercy is ſuch, <hi>that in the time of Tribulation thou forgiveſt them, that call upon thee) to thee, O Lord, I turn my Face, to thee I direct my Eyes. And now, Lord, be mindful of me, and take not Revenge of my Sins: but let thy Mercy quickly prevent me—Be merciful to my Sins for thy Names ſake: For not in my Juſtifications do I proſtrate Prayers before thy Face, but in thy many Commiſerations. Now therefore hear, O God, the Petition of thy Servant, and his Prayers — for thy own ſake.</hi> 1 Eſdr. 9. Tob. 3. Pſ. 78. Dan. 9.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:45075:45"/>
               <p n="4">4. Make your Intention to Honour God, by Praying in Union of Spirit with the Prayers and Praiſes of the Church Militant and Triumphant, for the general Good of Chriſt's whole Myſtical Body, and for ſome particular Benefit to your ſelf [<hi>e. g.</hi> the Overcoming of ſuch a Vice, the Obtaining of ſuch a Vertue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] according to the Exigency of your Preſent Spititual Neceſſities, <hi>James</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Cave the Divine Aid, that you may Pray well, and without Diſtractions, purpoſing ſtedfaſtly, by the Grace of God, not to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any willingly, and for that end ſay,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Open, O Lord, my Mouth, to bleſs thy Holy Name: Cleanſe alſo my Heart from all Vain, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and Wandring Thoughts: Enlighten my Underſtanding, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame my Affections, [and recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect my Senſes] that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite this Office [or theſe Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons] Worthily, Attentively, and Devoutly, and may deſerve to be
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45075:46"/>heard in Preſence of thy Divine Majeſty. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lord, in Union of that Divine Intention, with which thou, on Earth, didſt Praiſe God, I preſent theſe Hours [or Prayers] unto thee.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§ II. <hi>In</hi> Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Attention, Devotion,</hi> and <hi>Reverence,</hi> are Indiſpenſibly requiſite; and,</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Attention</hi> is a ſerious Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mind to the Senſe of the Words, ſo as to underſtand what you read, and know what you ask.</p>
               <p>And this is to <hi>Pray in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15.</p>
               <p>Now, for Procuring and Securing of this Attention,</p>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt pronounce your Words, not haſtily, and in a hurry, but leiſurely, and plainly, ſo that your ſelf may hear them diſtinctly; but you muſt not be over-loud in Company, leſt you diſtract others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You muſt take Care to keep your Thoughts free from Worldly Buſineſs, Vain Curioſities, and Idle
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:45075:46"/>Fancies, by recalling your Mind from Earth to Heaven, as often and as ſoon as you perceive it wandring and ſtraying abroad; and by making a Pauſe now and then, for Recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting your ſelf, and Renewing your Attention to the Preſence of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your Exterior Senſes muſt likewiſe be diligently guarded, that neither your Ears may hear, nor your Eyes behold the Vanities, to the Diſcompoſure of your Mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> All other Cauſes and Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of Diſtractions muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully avoided; otherwiſe your Prayers will not pleaſe, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>H. <hi>Devotion</hi> conſiſts in exciting and producing Affections of the Heart, ſuitable to the Senſes of the Words you repeat. Thus for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in reading the <hi>Pſalms,</hi>
[which make up the major part of Church-Offices], your Hearts muſt keep pace with your Mouths, and your Affections muſt correſpond to the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>'s Expreſſions;
<q>By Fearing, where he Fears; by Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:45075:47"/>where he Loves; by Praiſing, where he Praiſes; by Sorrowing, where he Sorrows; by Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where he Petitions; by Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling your ſelves, where he Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges his own Vileneſs; by giving Thanks for Benefits beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Chriſtians Spiritually, which he relates to have been conferr'd on the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Corporally, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Thus teaches S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> on <hi>Pſ.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>Therefore after this manner <hi>let us lift up our</hi> [Voices and] <hi>Hands to our Lord in the Heavens</hi> 
                  <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Lam. 3.41.</note>, and <hi>Pour ye out your Hearts before him</hi> 
                  <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Pſal. 61.9.</note>, that ſo you may <hi>Pray in Spirit</hi> with S. <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <note n="(c)" place="bottom">1 Cor. 14.15.</note>, and not incurr the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of Heaven with thoſe Inſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Devotes, whom God Almighty Reproves, ſaying, <hi>This People ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches with their Mouth, and with their Lips glorifies me: but their Heart is far from me.</hi> Iſa. 29.13.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Reverence</hi> conſiſts in ſuch Dreſs, Poſture, and Comportment
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:45075:47"/>of Body, as may moſt promote At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Devotion, and may qualifie you beſt for teſtifying an Humble Subjection to, and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the Majeſty of God: Like that of the <hi>Publican, who ſtanding afar off, would not ſo much as lift his Eyes toward Heaven; but knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Breaſt, ſaying, God be merciful to me a Sinner <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Luk. 18.13.</note>. For the Prayer of him that Humbles himſelf</hi> [thus] <hi>ſhall pierce the Clouds</hi> 
                  <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Ecclus 35.19. See Pſ. 101.18.</note>.</p>
               <p>But all ſuch Exterior Carriage and Actions muſt be utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, as diminiſh rather than en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe <hi>Attention,</hi> as ſavour more of Humour than <hi>Devotion,</hi> and as are Inconſiſtent with that <hi>Reverence,</hi> which is required at Prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III. <hi>After</hi> Prayer.</head>
               <p>The End crowns the Work of Prayer; the Fruit and Merit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of depends much on its Beginning, more on its Progreſs, and moſt on
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45075:48"/>its End: And therefore, <hi>better is the end of Prayer, than the beginning.</hi> Eccleſ. 7.9.</p>
               <p>Hence, to conclude your Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions well,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Examine briefly how you have behaved your ſelf, as to <hi>Attention, Devotion,</hi> and <hi>Reverence:</hi> And if well, give Thanks to God; but if negligently, crave Pardon, reſolve to Amend, and mark the Cauſe of your Miſ-behaviour, that you may avoid it for the future.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Offer to God your Devotions, (how imperfect ſoever) humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him to ſupply all their Defects (thro' the Merits of Chriſt, of the B. Virgin, and of all the Saints) and to accept thereof, for the end you propoſed to your ſelf, when you began them, as follows:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Accept, moſt merciful God, the Office of our Service: And if we have done any thing Praiſe-worthy, favourably regard it; and what is done Negligently, in Mildneſs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: Who in perfect Trinity
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45075:48"/>Liveſt and Reigneſt God, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Beſides <hi>Vocal</hi> Prayer (of which this Chapter treats), there is another kind of Prayer, termed <hi>Mental,</hi> which conſiſts of Three Triple Parts:</p>
               <p>The Firſt Part is <hi>Preparation,</hi> which includes,
<list>
                     <item>1. The Preſence of God.</item>
                     <item>2. Invocation of the Divine Aid.</item>
                     <item>3. Repreſentation of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Second Part is <hi>Meditation,</hi> which comprehends,
<list>
                     <item>1. Conſiderations.</item>
                     <item>2. Affections.</item>
                     <item>3. Reſolutions.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Third Part is the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> which contains,
<list>
                     <item>1. Thankſgiving.</item>
                     <item>2. Oblation.</item>
                     <item>3. Petition, and a Spiritual Noſegay.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the Underſtanding and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all which, I refer you to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:45075:49"/>the <hi>Introduction to a Devout Life.</hi> Part 2. Chap. 2. and Sect. 1.</p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Thus muſt you Pray [either <hi>Vocally,</hi> or <hi>Mentally</hi>] every Day, (both Morning and Evening <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 91.2.</note>) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hearty Addreſſes to <hi>God,</hi> who is <hi>Rich</hi> [in Bounty] <hi>towards all that Invocate him.</hi> Rom. 10.12. But never expect the Bleſſings of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, unleſs you ſet apart a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Time for asking them both Early and Late <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 26.9.</note>, even amidſt your fulleſt Worldly Employments.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of</hi> Hearing Maſs.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>In every Place there is Sacrificing, and there is offer'd to my Name a clean Oblation: Becauſe my Name is great among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſays the Lord of Hoſts. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mal. 1.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MASS (the Supreme Act of Chriſtian Religion) is the
<pb facs="tcp:45075:49"/>Unbloody Sacrifice of Chriſt's Body and Blood, Conſecrated and Offer'd to God, (under the outward Forms of Bread and Wine, with divers Ceremonies, Prayers, and Sacred Words) for the Quick and the Dead; to whom it applies the Merits of the Bloody Sacrifice of the Croſs.</p>
            <p>And as it was prefigured by the Sacrince of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Gen. 14.18. Pſ. 109.4. Heb. 5.10. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>v. laſt. c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 11, 15, 17.</note>, ſo it was Inſtituted by Chriſt himſelf, as to its <hi>Subſtance,</hi> in his laſt Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Mat. 26.26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Luk. 22.19.</note>; and as to its <hi>Ceremonies, &amp;c.</hi> by the Apoſtles and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 22. cap. 1, 4, 5.</note>. Again, as the Faithful, both Quick and Dead, were Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by the <hi>Carnal-unclean Sacrifices</hi> of Beaſts offer'd for them in the Old-Teſtament <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Lev. 1, 3, 4. 2 Mach. 12.43. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>; ſo (and much more) are they help'd in the New-Teſtament, by the <hi>Spiritual and Clean Oblation</hi> of Chriſt's Body and Blood <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 22. cap. 2.</note>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45075:50"/>
            <p>This therefore being of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Myſteries the moſt Sacred and Divine, it ought to be Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated and Aſſiſted at with all poſſible Diligence and Devotion; otherwiſe we ſhall bring upon our Heads a Curſe, inſtead of a Bleſſing: Becauſe, <hi>Accurſed is he, that does the Work of God negligently.</hi> Jer. 48.10.</p>
            <p>To hear <hi>Maſs</hi> then, as you ought, your Thoughts and Affections muſt correſpond to the Prieſt's Words and Actions; either by Reading with Attention and Devotion the <hi>Prayers at Maſs in the Manual;</hi> or by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the <hi>Offices and Devotions in the Primer</hi> to the <hi>Maſs,</hi> as follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Entring into the Church or Chappel, ſay, <hi>O Lord, in the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> &amp;c. Next, taking H. Water, ſay, (with Contrition for your Sins), <hi>Thou ſhalt ſprinkle,</hi> &amp;c. Then kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down Reſpectfully, as in the Preſence of God, ſay the Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Maſs, <hi>viz. O moſt Clement Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. as in the <hi>Daily Exerciſe.</hi> After which, make your Intention thus:</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:45075:50"/>
            <q>
               <p>Together with all the <hi>Maſſes</hi> that have been, are, and ſhall be ſaid throughout the whole World, I do here offer to thee, my God, this H. Sacrifice, with the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Deareſt Saviour, and his Holy Church, in Honour and Acknowledgment of thy Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and Dominion over me, and all Creatures; in Memory of my Saviour's Humanity and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; in Commemoration of his B. Virgin-Mother, and of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ints of this Solemnity; of <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> my H. Patrons, and of all the Saints in Heaven; in Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for all thy Benefits; in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Propitiation for my Sins; for obtaining thy Grace, and ſpecial Aid, in Proportion to my Preſent Neceſſities, <hi>[here ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your Spiritual Wants];</hi> and for prevailing with thy Goodneſs, to Protect and Bleſs me, thy Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Creature, my Relations, Benefactors, <hi>&amp;c. <note place="margin">Luk. 1.74, 75.</note> That without Fear, being deliver'd from the Hand of our Enemies, we may ſerve thee
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45075:51"/>in Holineſs and Juſtice, all our Days,</hi> and may at laſt Die in thy Favour.</p>
               <p>I offer alſo this Sacrifice to thee, Dear Lord, for all that Died in Unity of the Catholick Church, and particularly for the Souls of my Parents, Relations, Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and all thoſe, for whom thou wouldſt have me offer it. Eternal Reſt give unto them, O Lord, and let Perpetual Light ſhine to them.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="2">2. At the <hi>Beginning of Maſs,</hi> call to Mind the moſt grievous Sins, of which you have been, and are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and, in the Spirit of Humility and Repentance, ſay along with the Clerk, <hi>Confiteor Deo,</hi> &amp;c. or, <hi>I confeſs to Almighty God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. While the Prieſt reads the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects,</hi> read you the <hi>Antiphon, Verſe, Reſponſe</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> for the Day, either <hi>Proper,</hi> or <hi>Common,</hi> as you find them towards the end of the <hi>Primer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. At the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> (having read it at Home in <hi>Engliſh</hi>) reflect upon ſome Sentence thereof, or upon one
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45075:51"/>of the Eight Beatitudes, or any other Point of Chriſt's Doctrine; and, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him Thanks for the ſame, pray for Grace to practice it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. While the Prieſt ſays, <hi>Credo in Deum,</hi> &amp;c. ſay you, <hi>I believe in God,</hi> &amp;c. and pray, that you Live and Die in the Catholick Faith.</p>
            <p n="6">6. At the <hi>Offertory</hi> of the Bread and Wine, offer therewith to God your Body, Soul, Life, Health, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſeeching him ſo to Sanctifie them, that you may be <hi>a Living Sacrifice, Holy, and Acceptable to him.</hi> Rom. 12.1.</p>
            <p n="7">7. After <hi>Sanctus,</hi> whilſt the Prieſt makes his <hi>Memento</hi> for the Living, read you the Prayers for the <hi>Church,</hi> for the <hi>Chief Biſhop,</hi> for the <hi>King,</hi> for <hi>Hereticks,</hi> for <hi>Friends,</hi> for <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe you'll find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Prayers to be ſaid after the Litanies, according to the Diverſity of Times,</hi> and amongſt thoſe, that are Appointed for <hi>Invocating the Grace of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. At the <hi>Elevation,</hi> (1ſt,) of the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> ſay, <hi>Hail true Body,</hi> &amp;c. as
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:45075:52"/>in the <hi>Daily Exerciſe.</hi> (2dly,) Of the <hi>Chalice,</hi> ſay, Hail true Blood of my Lord and Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt, and of the New-Teſtament that was ſhed for me, and all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to the Remiſſion of our Sins <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 26.28.</note>: Cleanſe, Sanctifie, and keep my Soul, I beſeech thee, to Everlaſting Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And theſe two Addreſſes you muſt ſay by Heart, your Book being laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, during the Elevation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Soon after the Elevation follows the <hi>Memento</hi> for the Dead: Whilſt the Prieſt makes it, read you the Three firſt Prayers at the end of the <hi>Office for the Dead,</hi> with the <hi>Prayer for either, or both of your Deceaſed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> and <hi>for ſome particular Friend,</hi> either Man or Woman, departed; according to your Duty and Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in this Kind.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Say the <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> with the Prieſt, either in Latin, or Engliſh.</p>
            <p n="11">11. At <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> &amp;c. conſider Chriſt Jeſus as an Innocent Lamb, Slain (on the Croſs Really, and on the Altar Myſtically) to take away
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:45075:52"/>the Sins of the World, and beſeech him to diſcharge you of all your Failings, and eſpecially of thoſe you are moſt ſubject to.</p>
            <p n="12">12. At <hi>Domine, non ſum Dignus,</hi> &amp;c, <note place="margin">Mat. 15.27.</note> put on the Humility of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanean</hi> Woman, acknowledging your ſelf Unworthy of the Bread, yet deſirous of the Crumbs of your Maſter's Table, and ſay, <hi>Lord, I am not worthy,</hi> &amp;c. Then make your Spiritual Communion thus:</p>
            <p>
               <q>B. Saviour, I believe, that thou art Really preſent in this H. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: I hope, that thou wilt make me a Partaker of the Effects of this Divine Food: I love thee above all things, who haſt Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled thy ſelf ſo low, as to put thy ſelf under the Form of a little Bread, for Love of me; and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing more, than to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably united to thee, by Grace here, and by Glory hereafter.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. At the <hi>Poſt Communion,</hi> read the Anthem, <hi>O Sacred Banquet!</hi> &amp;c. with the Prayer, <hi>O God, who under,</hi> &amp;c. as before, Chap. V. § III.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:45075:53"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Read S. <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Goſpel</hi> with the Prieſt, as at the Beginning of the <hi>Primer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After <hi>Maſs,</hi> give Thanks to Chriſt for ſo great a Benefit, and for his Paſſion and Death repreſented and applied to us thereby; intreat him to Aſſiſt you in all your Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings that Day, and Daily: Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as after Prayer, Chap. XII. § III. And depart with due Reſpect and Reverence to the Altar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> In the foregoing Points you muſt keep pace exactly with the Prieſt: And when any one of them is not ſufficient for your Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, until he comes to the next in courſe, you may make out, by Reading the <hi>Prayers, or Meditations of the Paſſion of our Lord,</hi> which ſollow the Prayers after Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating: Thoſe Devotions being moſt proper for the Time and Place, wherein a moſt Lively and Life-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Memorial, and Repreſentation of Chriſt's Death, is made, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:45075:53"/>
            <p>For other Methods of Hearing Maſs, ſee a Treatiſe, named, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and Devotions for Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> The Church obliges the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Hear Maſs upon all <hi>Sundays</hi> and Holy-Days of Obligation; and the Omiſſion of ſo Important a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is a Mortal Sin, unleſs ſome Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Impediment excuſes it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of</hi> Hearing Sermons.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Bleſſed are they, that Hear the Word of God, and Keep it. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 11.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§ I. <hi>Before</hi> Sermon.</head>
               <p>HUmbly crave Grace of God, that you may profit by it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Lord, ſhew me thy Ways, and teach me thy Paths; direct me in thy Truth, and teach me.</hi> Grant, that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:45075:54"/>I may be none of thoſe, <hi>that hear, and have thy Word taken out of their Heart by the Devil, leſt believing they be ſaved;</hi> nor of thoſe, <hi>that when they hear, with Joy receive thy Word, and for a time believe, but in the time of Tentation</hi> [or Trial] <hi>do revolt;</hi> nor of thoſe, <hi>that have heard, and going their ways, are choaked with Cares and Riches, and the Pleaſures of this Life, and yield no Fruit:</hi> But make thou me one of their Number, <hi>who, in a very good Heart, hearing thy Word, do retain it, and yield Fruit in Patience.</hi> Pſ. 24.4, 5. Luk. 8.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§ II. <hi>At</hi> Sermon.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Look upon, and regard the Preacher, <hi>as an Angel of God,</hi> or <hi>as Chriſt himſelf.</hi> Gal. 4.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As an Angel of God;</hi> in regard 'tis written, <hi>that the Lips of the Prieſt ſhall keep Knowledge, and the Law they</hi> [Lay-People] <hi>ſhall require from his Mouth: becauſe he is the Angel of the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Mal. 2.7.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:45075:54"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>As Chriſt Jeſus himſelf;</hi> becauſe He ſays, <hi>He that hears you,</hi> [my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters] <hi>hears me; and he that deſpiſes you, deſpiſes me,</hi> &amp;c. Luk. 10.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mark not <hi>How,</hi> but <hi>What</hi> he ſpeaks; <hi>and receive it, not as the Word of Men, but (as it is indeed) the Word of God.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2.12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be attentive throughout, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to your ſelf (and not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) what the Preacher ſays; and fail not to lay up in the Store-houſe of your Memory, ſuch Inſtructions and Examples, as ſhall ſeem moſt uſeful and neceſſary, either for your preſent Diſengagement from Vice, or your future Improvement in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, with an Intention and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to put your Remarks in Practice, as Occaſion ſhall ſerve. <hi>A Man of Knowledge will praiſe whatſoever wiſe Word,</hi> [or Saying] <hi>he ſhall hear, and will apply it to himſelf: The Riotous Man has heard it, and it ſhall diſpleaſe him, and he will caſt it behind his Back,</hi> Ecclus 21.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:45075:55"/>
               <head>§ III. <hi>After</hi> Sermon.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Give Thanks to God for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Holy Will known to you: <hi>He has not done in like manner to every Nation; his Judgments he has not manifeſted to them,</hi> [ſo as to you], Pſ. 147.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beg Grace that you may do his H. Will proportionably to your Knowledge thereof; becauſe <hi>to one knowing to do Good, and not doing it, to him it is Sin,</hi> and the juſt Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a more heavy Doom. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.47, 48.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Begin forthwith to be ſuch Men, as the Sermon taught you to be; becauſe, <hi>Not the Hearers of the Law are juſt with God, but the Doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified. Be Doers</hi> therefore <hi>of the Word, and not Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers only, deceiving your ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For not the Forgetful Hearer</hi> [of the Word], <hi>but Doer of the Work, ſhall be bleſſed in his Deed,</hi> Rom. 2.13. Jam. 1.22. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:45075:55"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of Reading</hi> Pious Books.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>He that Reads, let him <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand, <hi>[both what he Reads, and how to Profit by it].</hi>
               </q>
               <bibl>Mat. <hi>24.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§ I. <hi>Before</hi> Reading.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen we Pray, we Speak to God; but when we Read, God Speaks to us.</hi> S. <hi>Aug.</hi> on <hi>Pſ.</hi> 65. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when you are about to Read, imagine you hear a Voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaying to you, (as formerly to S. <hi>Aug.</hi>) <hi>Tolle, Lege; Take up, and Read. Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 12. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly opening your Book, eſteem the Chapter, you are about to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe, as an Epiſtle or Letter ſent you from God; and pray for Grace to underſtand and practice it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Speak, Lord, for thy Servant Hears.</hi> 1 Kin. 3.9. <hi>Lord, give me <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and I will ſearch thy Law, and I will keep it with my
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:45075:56"/>whole Heart,</hi> Pſ. 118.34. <hi>Give what thou Commandeſt, and Command what thou pleaſeſt.</hi> S. Aug. Lib. 10. Conf. c. 31.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§ II. <hi>In</hi> Reading.</head>
               <p>Read out of a Deſire to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more Vertuous, rather than more Knowing; becauſe <hi>Knowledge puffs up, but Charity edifies,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Read, not haſtily, but leiſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; nor much at a time, but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle at once, with much Attention.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As often as you meet with a Point, that may contribute to the better ordering of your Life, pauſe there, and digeſt it well before you paſs any further, conſidering when and where you ſhall have occaſion to practiſe it; that ſo you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch an one, as that Point re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires you to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§ III. <hi>After</hi> Reading.</head>
               <p>Give Thanks, beg Grace, as after Sermon, and be ſure to put in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution the Leſſon you Read, by
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:45075:56"/>doing what it Recommends, and by refraining what it Reproves, upon <hi>ſuch and ſuch</hi> Occaſions; otherwiſe your Reading will be as Vain and Fruitleſs, as Hearing good things, and not Practiſing them. Chap. XIV. § III. N. 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="*⁎*">
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Read Daily (at your beſt Convenience) in <hi>Chriſtian Thoughts,</hi> what is appointed for the preſent Day of the Month; and in Reading and Practiſing, obſerve the Method preſcribed in the Author's Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement. Thus much both may and ought to be done by Perſons of the fulleſt Employ. But to ſuch as have more Leiſure, and ſpare Time, I recommend the Four Books of <hi>Inſtructions for the whole Year,</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly exhorting them to let no Day paſs, without the Peruſal and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of its proper Leſſon, that ſo their Devotions and Actions may keep Pace exactly with the Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Examples, propoſed by the Church in her Daily different Maſſes and Offices.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:45075:57"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of</hi> Holy Proceſſions.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>We march towards the Place which our Lord will give us. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 10.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>PUblic and Sacred Proceſſions, or Supplications, were Antiently Inſtituted by the H. Fathers, and are now commonly uſed by the Church, either for Exciting the Piety of the Faithful, or for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of God's Benefits, and giving him Thanks, or for Implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Divine Aid. Hence they contain Great and Godly Myſteries, and the Devout Practiſers of them obtain of God wholeſom Fruits of Chriſtian Piety, and therefore ought to be Solemnized with due Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Devotion.</p>
            <p>Theſe walking Devotions ſignifie, in general, our Pilgrimage on Earth towards Heaven; of which, S. <hi>Paul</hi> writes thus; <hi>We have not here a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:45075:57"/>Permanent City</hi> [or laſting abode], <hi>but we ſeek for that which is to come; knowing, that while we are in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, we are Pilgrims from God; for we walk by Faith, not by Sight.</hi> Heb. 13.14. 2 Cor. 5.7.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Proceſſions, the <hi>Croſs</hi> is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out firſt, to ſignifie how <hi>Jeſus alſo, that he might Sanctifie the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by his own Blood, ſuffer'd without the Gate</hi> [<hi>of</hi> Jeruſalem]; and that, <hi>ſo it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and ſo to enter into his Glory.</hi> Heb. 13.12. and Luk. 24. v. 26, and 46.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next to the <hi>Croſs,</hi> are carried the <hi>Images and Relicks of Saints,</hi> to ſignifie, that by way of the <hi>Croſs</hi> they came to the Crown of Glory, and that we alſo muſt hold the ſame Road, to arrive at the ſame Happineſs, as Chriſt himſelf aſſures us, ſaying, <hi>If any Man will come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me, let him deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs daily, and follow me.</hi> Luk. 9.23. See alſo <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 27. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us go therefore to him, without the Camp, carrying his Reproach. Let
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:45075:58"/>us ſuffer with him, that we may be alſo glorified with Him. For if we ſhall ſuſtain, we ſhall alſo Reign together.</hi> Heb. 13.13. Rom. 8.17. 2 Tim. 2.12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After theſe, is carried the <hi>B. Sacrament</hi> of Chriſt's Body, the Heavenly Food of our Souls, and the Support of our Spiritual Life in this our Earthly Pilgrimage. See Chap. VII. § I.</p>
            <p>At Proceſſions, Lay-People muſt march apart from the Clergy, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from Men, in decent Attire, Gravely, Modeſtly, and Devoutly; entertaining themſelves with God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thoughts and Prayers (without Laughing, Talking, and Gazing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) and joining Hearts and Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with the Clergy, in <hi>Thanksgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> for paſt Benefits, in <hi>Craving</hi> of future Bleſſings, in <hi>Deploring</hi> of preſent Public Calamities, (the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and Puniſhments of Sin
<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 14.34. Iſa. 24.5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>), and in <hi>Imploring</hi> of God's Mercy, according to the Reſpective End and Intent of each Proceſſion. And,</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:45075:58"/>
            <p>Amongſt other Pious Thoughts and Expreſſions, they may uſe theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are Pilgrims before thee, O Lord, and Strangers, as all our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers</hi> [have been]: <hi>Our Days are as a Shadow upon the Earth, and there is no abiding</hi> [here for us]
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">1 Par. 29.15.</note>. <hi>Hear my Prayer, O Lord, and my Petition: With thy Ears receive my Tears, becauſe I am a Stranger with thee, and a Pilgrim, as my Fathers. Forgive me, that I may be Refreſhed before I Depart, and ſhall be no more
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Pſ. 38.13.</note>. Wo is me, that my Sojourning is prolonged. —My Soul has been long a Sojourner, <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Pſal. 119.5.</note> having a deſire to be Diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, a thing much better, than to abide in the Fleſh.</hi> Phil. 1.23. See alſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For they, that ſay theſe things, do ſignifie, that they ſeek a Countrey, and deſire a better</hi> [than this], <hi>that is to ſay, a Heavenly one.</hi> Heb. 11.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:45075:59"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Of</hi> Viſiting <hi>the</hi> Sick.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Want not in Conſolation to them that weep; and walk with them that Mourn: Be not loth to Viſit the Sick, for by theſe things thou ſhalt be Confirm'd in Love. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ecclus 7.38, 39.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD has given to every one change of his Neighbour.</hi> Ecclus 17.12. Of which Charge a principal part is Viſiting and Aſſiſting the Sick. Therefore as ſoon as you hear of your Neighbour being fall'n Sick, go freely to Viſit him, and Exerciſe your Charity often, during his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity.</p>
            <p>And whilſt you are on your way to the Sick, conſider the Charity, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with which Chriſt uſed to Viſit and Comfort Sick and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Perſons: Beſeech him to Animate you with his Spirit, that you may diſcharge this Duty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:45075:59"/>to the Pattern he has ſet you; and at the ſame time offer to him the Action you are going to perform, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you come to the Sick, by Charitable Compaſſion take part in his (or her) Sufferings, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make them Eaſie and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious by Godly Reading, Good Counſel, and Devout Prayer. And,</p>
            <p>§ I. Every Viſit you make, Read what you judge moſt proper for the Sick Perſon's Inſtruction, Comfort, and Encouragement, either out of <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s <hi>Art of Dying Well,</hi> or the <hi>Preparation for Death,</hi> collected by <hi>Ballentine,</hi> or the <hi>Holy Deſires of Death,</hi> or the Exerciſes preparatory for Death, at the end, (1.) Of the <hi>Chriſtian Rules.</hi> (2.) Of the <hi>Manual of the Poor Man's Devotions.</hi> (3.) Of the <hi>Daily Exerciſe of a Chriſtian Life.</hi> (4.) Of the <hi>Daily Exerciſe of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Chriſtian:</hi> Or, you may Read the <hi>Paſſion of our Saviour</hi> (according to one of the Four Evangeliſts) in the <hi>Primer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:45075:60"/>
            <p>§ II. The Counſel you are to give the Sick Man, muſt regard, 1. His <hi>Eſtate:</hi> 2. His <hi>Body:</hi> And 3. His <hi>Soul:</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to his <hi>Eſtate:</hi> At the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his Sickneſs (if he has not done it beforehand) you muſt perſwade him to make his Laſt Will and Teſtament
<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 38.1.</note>; and in Settling his Temporal Concerns, advertiſe him, (1.) To Pay his Debts, and Reſtore what belongs to others. (2.) To leave to his Heir what is his due. (3.) To beſtow Alms on the Poor, and eſpecially on his Needy Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. (4.) To give ſomething that his Soul may be remembred at the Altar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that he may be ſure of ſome Performance in this kind, Admoniſh him to make his own Hands Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors in part, according to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Son, if thou haſt it do good to</hi> Thy Self, <hi>and offer to</hi> God <hi>worthy Oblations. —Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Death do good to</hi> Thy Friend, <hi>and according to thy Ability, ſtretching
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:45075:60"/>out thy Hand, give to the</hi> Poor. —<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy Death work Juſtice.</hi> Ecclus 14.11, <hi>&amp;c. And I</hi> (adds Chriſt) <hi>ſay unto you, Make to your ſelves Friends of the Mammon of Iniquity,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> of Riches, the Idol of World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings]; <hi>that, when you fail, they may receive you into the Eternal Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles.</hi> Luk. 16.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And to his <hi>Body:</hi> Admoniſh him to Surrender it entirely unto the Care and Management of his Phyſician, ſaying, <hi>Honour the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician for neceſſity; for the Higheſt has Created him: for all Medicine is of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Higheſt has Created Medicines of the Earth, and a Wiſe Man will not abhor them. The Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of theſe things is come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Men, and the Higheſt has given knowledge to Man, for to be honour'd in his Marvellous things. Curing with theſe things, he ſhall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate Pain,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Give place to the Phyſician, and let him not depart from thee, becauſe his Works are neceſſary. —And they</hi> [that practice Phyſick]
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:45075:61"/>
               <hi>ſhall beſeech our Lord, that he direct their Cure.</hi> Ecclus 38. <hi>paſſimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let Phyſicians beware of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing or Applying any thing for the Cure of the Body, that may be hurtful to the Soul: And let them not make above Three Viſits to the Sick, unleſs they be firſt Certified, that their Patients have duly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated their Sins by Sacramental Confeſſion: For ſo the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and many Popes, have De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed under great Penalties.</p>
            <p>If the Sick Party be deſtitute of Corporal Neceſſaries, and an Object of Charity, do not neglect the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of him out of your own Purſe, or Stores, as far as you are able, like the good <hi>Samaritan. Luk.</hi> 10. And, if that will not ſuffice, then you muſt take Care to make his Wants known, that they may be Supplied by Private or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Collections of Alms.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to his <hi>Soul:</hi> You muſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe him; that Sickneſs and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes are many times the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sin, mercifully inflicted by
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:45075:61"/>Almighty God for the Reclaiming of Sinners. This Holy Writ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, ſaying, <hi>He that Sins in his ſight that Made him, ſhall fall into the Hands of the Phyſician.</hi> Eccl. 38.15. <hi>He</hi> [God] <hi>rebukes alſo by Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in the Bed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim their Souls from Corruption,</hi> &amp;c. Job 33.19.30. <hi>O how ſweet is thy Spirit, O Lord, in all! And therefore thoſe, that err, by parts thou doſt Chaſtiſe, and doſt Admoniſh, and Speak to them concerning the things, wherein they Sin: That, leaving naughtineſs, they may believe in thee;</hi> and when nothing elſe will reclaim them, it often happens, that <hi>a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Infirmity makes a ſober Soul.</hi> Wiſd. 12.1, 2. Ecclus 31.2.</p>
            <p>In which Caſe, Sin being taken away by true Repentance, Sickneſs alſo ceaſes, and not otherwiſe; as it appears in that King <hi>Ezechias,</hi> (when Sick even to Death) <hi>by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Tears obtain'd of God Health and longer Life;</hi> whereas King <hi>Aſa</hi> fell Sick and <hi>Died</hi> of a moſt violent Pain in his Feet, becauſe <hi>in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:45075:62"/>he did not ſeek our Lord, but truſted in the Art of Phyſicians.</hi> 4 K. 20.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 38.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Paral. 16.12, 13.</p>
            <p>Hence, addreſs your ſelf to your Sick Neighbour after this manner; <hi>Son, in thy Infirmity contemn not thy ſelf, but pray to our Lord, and he will Cure thee. Turn away from Sin, and direct thy Hands, and from all Offence cleanſe thy Heart.</hi> Ecclus 38.9, 10. That is to ſay, Repent for thy Sins, Implore the Divine Mercy, Place all thy Hope in God, Endure patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Pains of thy Corporal Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in Satisfaction for thy Sins, look upon it as a Fatherly Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Chaſſiſement of God, leſs than thy Sins deſerve, and believe it befals thee for the good of thy Soul, and the Amendment of thy Life. <hi>Judith</hi> 8.27. <hi>Job</hi> 33. <hi>from v.</hi> 19. <hi>to v.</hi> 31. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 102.10, 13, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But if his Sickneſs grows Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, you muſt Admoniſh him to procure in due time, what farther Helps are requiſite for the Salvation of his Soul, and that with all fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:45075:62"/>expedition he ſend for his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Director, and impart to him, in Confeſſion, his Sins, Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Fears, in order to receive of him Abſolution, fit Remedies, and Encouragement; as alſo the Holy Sacraments of Euchariſt and Extreme Unction, whilſt his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Memory and Senſes are perfect; without thoſe dangerous and deceitful Delays, which (thro' the Falacy of the Devil) have brought, and Daily do bring many to endleſs Miſery.</p>
            <p>If the Sick Perſon will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to Confeſs his Sins, do not preſently give him over for loſt; but frequently (as long as he lives) be putting him in mind of the great Mercy of God inviting him to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and moſt ready to Pardon his Sins, if he will Confeſs them; and endeavour to make him ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, how (thro' Impenitence) he hazards his Salvation, and expoſes himſelf to Everlaſting Torments. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Moreover both Private and Publick Supplications
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:45075:63"/>muſt be made to God for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Salvation of a Soul at the Brink of Eternity, and ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably unprovided for it.</p>
            <p>You muſt take Care, that a Figure of Chriſt Crucified be ever placed in View of the Sick, and that Holy Water do always ſtand beſide him, wherewith he may be often ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; you muſt likewiſe propoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him (according to his condition) ſome ſhort Prayers and godly Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Mind; eſpecially ſome Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Pſalms, (ſet down in the next Chapter) our Lord's Prayer, the Angelical Salutation, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, the Meditation of our Lord's Paſſion, the Martyrdoms (or, Sufferings) of the Saints, the happy State of Heavenly Glory, which will abundantly Recompence all his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Grievances. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>But theſe things muſt be ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and diſcreetly Suggeſted, that they may not moleſt, but give eaſe to the Sick.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:45075:63"/>
            <p>§ III. Tell your Sick Neighbour for his Comfort, that you and the reſt of the Company will Pray for him: And accordingly (having firſt deſired that his Thoughts and Heart may go along with your Words) kneel down, and ſay the <hi>Prayers for the Sick,</hi> as in the <hi>Manual,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, Exhort him, if he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers, to go to Church the firſt Journey he takes, and there to give God Thanks for his Recovery, as alſo to receive Holy Communion Devoutly, and thenceforward to lead a better Courſe of Life: That being a Duty incumbent on every Chriſtian after his Recovery, no leſs than on the Bed-rid Man after his Cure; whom when Jeſus found in the Temple, he ſaid to him, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thou art made Whole; Sin no more, leſt ſome worſe thing chance to thee.</hi> Jo. 5.14.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:45075:64"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Of Aſſiſting</hi> Dying Perſons.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Comfort him <hi>[that lies a Dying],</hi> in the Departure of his Spirit. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ecclus 38.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>HE loves at all times, that is a Friend; and a Brother is proved in diſtreſſes.</hi> Prov. 17.17. But no time is of greater Conſequence, than the Hour of Death, and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Eternity; nor any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs comparable to our laſt Agony: Therefore he is our beſt Friend, and kindeſt Brother, who aſſiſts us moſt in thoſe our greateſt Extremities.</p>
            <p>Now the beſt Service you can do an Agonizing Perſon, is as follows.</p>
            <p>§ I. Admoniſh him to Pronounce often, with a Contrite Heart, the moſt Holy Name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and Help him (whilſt he is able) to make Acts of Faith, Hope, Charity, and other Vertues, after this manner.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:45075:64"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I Believe</hi> firmly all the Articles of Faith, which the Holy-Catholick-Apoſtolick and <hi>Roman</hi> Church Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves and Teaches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Hope</hi> that Chriſt our Lord, for his Immenſe Goodneſs, will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to me, and that I ſhall obtain Life Everlaſting, thro' the Merits of his moſt Holy Paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Love</hi> God with my whole Heart, and I deſire above all things to Love him, as the Angels and Saints in Heaven do Love him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am Sorry</hi> from my Heart, for the Love of God, that I ever Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him, or my Neighbour, in any kind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Pardon</hi> from my Heart, for the Love of God, all my Enemies, and thoſe that have any way Moleſted me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Crave Pardon</hi> of all thoſe I have at any time Offended, either in Word or Deed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Accept</hi> with Patience the Pain I Endure, and the Anguiſh of my Sickneſs, for God's ſake, in Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Expiation of my Sins.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:45075:65"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I Reſign</hi> my ſelf freely to the Pangs of Death, for the Love of him that Died upon the Croſs, to Save me from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dleſs Miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Reſolve,</hi> if God Reſtores my Health, to avoid Sin hereafter, and to keep his Commandments, as much as in me lies: And I would rather Die in the State I now am in, than Live to Offend my God any more.</p>
            <p>§ II. Exhort him to Pray (at leaſt in Heart) as often as he's able, after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Have Mercy on me, O God, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy great mercy.</hi> Pſal. 50.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In thee, O Lord, have I hoped: let me not be Confounded for ever.</hi> Pſal. 30.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Into thy hands, O Lord, I commend my Spirit: thou haſt redeemed me, O Lord, God of Truth.</hi> Pſal. 30.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O God, incline unto my Aid: O Lord, make haſte to help me.</hi> Pſal. 69.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be thou, Lord God, to me a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</hi> Pſal. 30.3.</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:45075:65"/>
            <p>
               <hi>God be Merciful to me a Sinner.</hi> Luk. 18.13.</p>
            <p>Moſt Sweet Lord Jeſus, in Virtue of thy Paſſion, receive me into the Number of thy Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt receive my Spirit.</hi> Acts 7.59.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary,</hi> Mother of Grace, Mother of Mercy, protect us from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and at the Hour of Death, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us.</p>
            <p>Angel-Guardian Aſſiſt me.</p>
            <p>All ye Holy Angels and Saints Intercede for me, and Succour me.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and ſuch like Prayers, you may ſuggeſt to a Dying Perſon, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Capacity.</p>
            <p>§ III. During his Agony, ſprinkle him with Holy Water, offer him the Crucifix to Kiſs; by Efficacious words put him in hopes of Eternal Life, and place the Crucifix before him, that in beholding it he may conceive hopes of his Salvation, thro' him who Died upon the Croſs.</p>
            <p>Admoniſh the Domeſticks and By-ſtanders to join with you in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:45075:66"/>Prayer for the Dying Party, and then, on your Knees read Devoutly the <hi>Recommendation of a Soul depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> as in the <hi>Manual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, when the Soul is at the point of leaving the Body, then all preſent muſt Pray moſt earneſtly for its happy Departure; and one of the Aſſiſtants applying his Mouth towards the Ear of the Perſon Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, muſt pronounce in a Hain and Comfortable Tone, <hi>Jeſu, Jeſu, Jeſu;</hi> and, as often as it ſhall ſeem fitting, he may repeat that Sacred Name, as alſo the following Sentences; <hi>Into thy Hands, O Lord, I commend my Spirit. Lord Jeſus Chriſt receive my Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. as before.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As ſoon as the Soul is gone out of the Body, Pray thus:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Succour ſpeedily, O ye Saints of God; haſten, O ye Angels of our Lord; receive this Soul, and offer it in Preſence of the Higheſt. May Jeſus Chriſt, who has call'd thee, receive thee, and may his Angels carry thee into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom. Eternal Reſt give her, O Lord,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:45075:66"/>and let perpetual Light ſhine unto her. Lord have Mercy on us, Chriſt have, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lord have, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our Father, <hi>&amp;c. Verſ.</hi> And lead us not, <hi>&amp;c. Reſp.</hi> But deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, <hi>&amp;c. V.</hi> From the Gate of Hell. <hi>R.</hi> O Lord deliver this Soul. <hi>V.</hi> Let her reſt in Peace. <hi>R.</hi> Amen. <hi>V.</hi> O Lord, hear my Prayer. <hi>R.</hi> And let my Cry come to thee.</p>
               <p>We recommend to thee, O Lord, the Soul of thy Servant <hi>N.</hi> that, being Dead to the World, he [or ſhe] may live to thee; and the Sins he [or ſhe] has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, thro' Frailty of Human Converſation, do thou mercifully Pardon and Wipe away: Thro' Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>In the Interim let thy Paſſing-Bell be rung according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Place; that they, who hear it, may pray for the Soul new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly departed. Afterwards let the Corps be order'd handſomly, and placed in a decent Room, with Candle-Light; and let a ſmall Croſs
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:45075:67"/>be ſet between the Hands, join'd on the Breaſt of the Dead Body; or for want of a Croſs, let its Hands be laid over one another, in form of a Croſs; and let it be ſprinkled with H. Water; and whilſt it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Houſe, let all preſent pray for the Soul of the Party de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Of</hi> Burying <hi>the</hi> Dead.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Bleſſed be you to our Lord, who have ſhewn Mercy to your Lord, <hi>Saul,</hi> and have Buried him: And now truly our Lord will render you Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Kings 2.5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl> See
<bibl>
                     <hi>Tob. 12.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN going to, and aſſiſting at Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, there is offer'd you an Opportunity to exerciſe Three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Acts of Charity, <hi>viz.</hi> Edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your ſelf, Comforting of the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:45075:67"/>Sorrowful, and Praying for the Dead. And,</p>
            <p>§ I. As to Edifying of your ſelf. There is no better a Preſervative a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sin, than the Remembrance of Death; and therefore 'tis writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>In all thy Works, remember thy laſt things, and thou ſhalt not Sin.</hi> Ecclus 7.40. Neither is there any livelier Memorial of Death, than a Funeral: Wherefore <hi>it is better to go to the Houſe of Mourning, than to the Houſe of Banqueting; for in that the end of all Men is ſignified; and he that lives, thinks what ſhall be.</hi> Eccleſ. 7.3.</p>
            <p>Hence, at Funerals, follow the Advice of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> viz. <hi>Son, upon the Dead ſhed Tears,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Diſcretion cover his Body, and neglect not his Burial:—Remember the laſt things, and forget not:</hi> [Imagin the deceaſed Party ſays to thee], <hi>Be mindful of my Judgment, for thine alſo muſt be ſo: To me Yeſterday, and to thee to Day.</hi> Ecclus 38.16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:45075:68"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For what is your Life? It is a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, appearing for a little while, and afterwards it ſhall vanquiſh away, and after Death, Judgment enſues.</hi> Jam. 4.14. Heb. 9.27. <hi>O that Men were wife and underſtood, and would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for their laſt things.</hi> Deut. 32.29.</p>
            <p>§ II. As to Comforting of the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful. <hi>Penſiveneſs in the Heart of a Man ſhall humble him, and with a good Word he ſhall be made glad.</hi> Prov. 12.25. Hence <hi>David</hi> ſent Meſſengers to comfort <hi>Hanon,</hi> upon the Death of his Father; and many of the <hi>Jews</hi> came to <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> to comfort them, concerning their Brother <hi>Lazarus,</hi> deceaſed. 1 <hi>Par.</hi> 19.2. <hi>John</hi> 11.19, 31.</p>
            <p>In like manner Chriſtians ought to comfort one another, (when in Sorrow for their deceaſed Relations and Friends) by putting them in Mind of the Spiritual Dangers we live in, and what a Mercy is it, to be in better Circumſtances: How happy are they, that are gotten well out of this miſerable Life. And tho'
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:45075:68"/>we be ſeparated from them at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the time will come, when we ſhall meet them again in Joy, without end. <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 4.10. <hi>&amp;c. Apoc.</hi> 14.13. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ III. As to Praying for the Dead. <hi>It is a Holy and Healthful Cogitation to pray for the Dead, that they may be looſed from Sins,</hi> and Puniſhments, remiſſible in the next World. 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 12.46. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.59. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>from the Dead ſtay not Grace</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Ecclus 7.37.</note>, but endeavour their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſment by Prayer, and other Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">2 Mach. 12.43, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.29.</note>; eſpecially whilſt the Corps is on its way to the Grave; and whilſt the Office and Maſs is ſaying for the Soul departed. And do this Charitable Duty ſo, as you could wiſh to have it done for you after your Deceaſe.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:45075:69"/>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> How Meritorious a Devotion it is to Bury the Dead Religiouſly, the Angel declared to <hi>Tobie,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>When thou didſt Pray with Tears, and didſt Bury the Dead,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd thy Prayers to our Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Tob. 12.12. See alſo 2 <hi>K.</hi> 2. above.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>Of</hi> Alms-giving.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Alms delivers from all Sin, and from Death, and will not ſuffer the Soul to go into Darkneſs.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Tob. 4.11.</hi>
                  </bibl> See alſo
<bibl>
                     <hi>c. 12. v. 9. Pſ. 40.2.</hi>
                  </bibl> &amp;c.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Dan. 4.24. Prov. 16.6. Ecclus 29.15,</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FOR the due Ordering and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation of your Charity, you muſt mark well, 1. In what <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> 2. In what <hi>Manner.</hi> 3. To what <hi>Perſons</hi> your Alms are to be given. And,</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:45075:69"/>
            <p n="1">I. As to the <hi>Meaſure. Of thy Subſtance give Alms, and turn not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy Face from any poor Perſon; for ſo it ſhall come to paſs, that neither the Face of our Lord ſhall be turned from thee. As thou ſhalt be able, ſo be merciful: If thou haſt much, give abundantly: If thou haſt little, ſtudy to impart alſo a little willingly.</hi> Tob. 4.7. And,</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>the juſt Man is merciful, and will give.</hi> Pſ. 36.21. becauſe <hi>the juſt Man</hi> (as the Gloſs) <hi>has always ſomething to give;</hi> as for Example, a Farthing
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Mar. 12.42.</note>, a Cup of cold Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Mat. 10.42.</note>, a Comfortable Word <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Chap. XIX. § II.</note>, or <hi>at leaſt a Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let no one ſay, I have not any thing to give, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ II. As to the <hi>Manner</hi> of giving, you muſt beſtow your Alms.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>With all poſſible Secrecy, and with an Intention to pleaſe,</hi> not Men, but <hi>God,</hi> Mat. 6.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:45075:70"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Readily;</hi> becauſe it is written, <hi>Do not prohibit him to do Good, that is able: If thou be able, thy ſelf alſo do Good: Say not to thy</hi> [Needy] <hi>Friend, Go, and return, and to Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row I will give to thee, whereas thou may'ſt give forthwith.</hi> Prov. 3.27, 28. <hi>Afflict not the Heart of the Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and defer not thy Gift to him that is in Diſtreſs.</hi> Ecclus 4.3. <hi>Qui cito dat, bis dat:</hi> A ſpeedy Alms is a double Charity, when it has for its Motive the ſpeedy Relief of the Neceſſitous: But when one gives quickly, that he may quit himſelf of the Importunity of his Petitioner, then he loſes both his Gift and its Merit; as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> has it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Courteouſly;</hi> becauſe it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Make thy ſelf effable to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Poor.—Bow down thy Ear to the Poor without Sadneſs, and pay thy Debt, and anſwer him peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Words in Mildneſs.</hi> Ecclus 4.7, 8. <hi>And when thou haſt given, upbraid not.</hi> Ecclus 41.28. <hi>In good Deeds give no Blame, and in every Gift give not the Sadneſs of an evil Word. Shall
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:45075:70"/>not Dew cool Heat? So alſo a Word better than a Gift. Is not a</hi> [good] <hi>Word above a good Gift? But both are with a Juſtified Man. A Fool will upbraid bitterly.</hi> Ecclus 18.15. &amp;c. <hi>The Gift of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwiſe ſhall not be Brofitable for thee:—He will give few things, and upbraid many; and the opening of his Mouth is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation,</hi> that does more Harm to the Soul, than his Gifts do Good to the Body of the diſtreſſed Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>Ecclus</hi> 20.14, 15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Cheerfully;</hi> becauſe it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>In every Gift make thy Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance cheerful.</hi> Ecclus 35.9. <hi>And let every one give as he has determin'd in his Heart, not of Sadneſs, or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: For God loves a cheerful Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> 2 Cor. 9.7.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>from the Poor turn not away thy Eyes for Anger; and leave not them that ask of thee, to curſe thee behind thy Back. For the Prayer of him, that curſes thee in the Bitterneſs of his Soul, ſhall be heard; and he that made him, will hear him.</hi> Eccleſ. 4.5, 6.</p>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:45075:71"/>
            <p>§ III. As to Perſons, on whom you may beſtow your Alms. <hi>If thou wilt do Good, know to whom thou doſt it. — Do Good to the Juſt, and thou ſhalt find great Reward; and if not of him, aſſuredly of our Lord.— Give not to the Wicked,</hi> that will abuſe thy Kindneſs, to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of God, his own, or his Neighbour's Harm: <hi>For thou ſhalt find double Evils in all the Good, whatſoever thou ſhalt do to him: Becauſe the Higheſt hates</hi> [Obſtinate] <hi>Sinners, and will repay Vengeance to to the Wicked.</hi> Ecclus 12.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, if you have reaſon to hope that your Kindneſs may be a Means to invite the Wicked to Goodneſs, then <hi>Be ye Merciful, as alſo your</hi> [Heavenly] <hi>Father is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful: Who makes his Sun to riſe upon the Good, and the Bad; and rains upon the Juſt, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt.</hi> Luk. 6.36. Mat. 5.45. <hi>And if thy Enemy Hunger, give him Meat; if he Thirſt, give him Drink. Be
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:45075:71"/>not overcome of Evil, but overcome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil with Good.</hi> Prov. 25.21, 22. Rom. 12.20, 21. And for that end, <hi>To every one, that asks, give.</hi> Luke 6.30. <hi>And whilſt we have time, let us do Good to all, but eſpecially to the Faithful,</hi> [Gal. 6.10.] as to Chriſt our Lord, who eſteems what's done to them, as done to himſelf. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40. See 1 John 3.17, 18.</p>
            <p>But what cannot be given to all, muſt be given to the more Needy; and if one be not more Needy than another, then chuſe by Lot to whom it muſt be given. S. <hi>Aug. de Doctr. Chriſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Of</hi> Faſting.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Sanctifie ye a Faſt. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joel. 1.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Conditions and Qualities of a Faſt, Holy and Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, are as follow.</p>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:45075:72"/>
            <p n="1">1. Your Faſting muſt proceed from a Sincere Converſion of the Heart, and an Intention to Appeaſe God's Wrath, and Satisfie his Juſtice in the Voluntary Confeſſion and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Sins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now therefore, ſays our Lord, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to me in all your Heart, in Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in Weeping, and in Mourning: Rent your Hearts, and not your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and turn to the Lord your God; becauſe he is Benign and Merciful, Patient, and of much Mercy, and ready to be Gracious upon the Malice</hi> [of Repenting Sinners]. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12, 13.</p>
            <p>In this Diſpoſition of Soul, the <hi>Iſraelites, Achab,</hi> and the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> Faſted, and Humbled themſelves; and thereupon God had Mercy on them. 1 <hi>K.</hi> 7.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3 <hi>K.</hi> 21.27, &amp;c. <hi>Jonas</hi> 3.5. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Your Faſting muſt be void of Self-will and Rigor towards others, and accompanied with Self-denial, and Works of Mercy.</p>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:45075:72"/>
            <p>When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> enquired why God Almighty regarded not their Faſting? The Prophet gave the Reaſon of their Diſappointment, ſaying, <hi>Behold, in the Day of your Faſt; your own Will is found, and you exact of all your Debtors: Behold you Faſt to Debates and Contentions, and ſtrike with the Fiſt Impiouſly. Do not Faſt, as until this Day, that your Cry may be heard on High: Is this ſuch a Faſt, as I have choſen?—Wilt thou call this a Faſt, and a Day ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the Lord? Is not this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Faſt that I have choſen? Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Bands of Iniquity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Break thy Bread to the Hungry and Needy, and the Harbourleſs bring into thy Houſe: When thou ſhalt ſee the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, cover him, and deſpiſe not thy Fleſh—.Then ſhalt thou Invocate, and our Lord will hear,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If thou wilt ceaſe to ſpeak that which profits not, and ſhalt fill the Afflicted Soul,—our Lord will give thee Reſt always, and will fill thy Soul with Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 58. See alſo <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tamur ergo Parcius,</hi> &amp;c. Let
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:45075:73"/>us therefore (on Faſt-Days) put a Reſtraint upon our Words, Meat, Drink, Sleep, Sports, and ſet a ſtricter Guard over our Senſes; let us avoid Sin, and the Occaſions thereof; let us exerciſe Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Your Faſting muſt be attended not only with <hi>Alms-deeds,</hi> but alſo with <hi>Prayer;</hi> its Individual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, on all Occaſions, and Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, when uſed with great Inſtance and Perſeverance. <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.8, 9, 18, 19. <hi>Tob.</hi> 3.10, <hi>&amp;c. Judith</hi> 4.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Prayer is good with Faſting and Alms,</hi> Tob. 12.8. And, <hi>as a triple Cord, is hardly broken,</hi> Eccleſ. 4.12. So theſe three Suffrages, duly linked together, are moſt prevalent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Your Faſting muſt be void of outward Shew, and as reſerved as poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When you Faſt</hi> (ſays Chriſt) <hi>be not, as Hypocrites, ſad; for they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure their Faces, that they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unto Men to Faſt. Amen I ſay to you, they have received their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. But thou, when thou doſt Faſt, Anoint thy Head, and Waſh thy Face,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:45075:73"/>that thou appear not to Men to Faſt, but to thy Father, who is in ſecret; and thy Father, who ſees in Secret, will repay thee.</hi> And like Privacy is to be obſerved in <hi>Alms-deeds</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> as you may ſee at large. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Read the Preface, and the Five next enſuing Paragraphs in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions for</hi> Lent, and they will give you a fuller Account of this Duty.</p>
            <p>The Church commands us to Faſt, <hi>Lent, Vigils</hi> or <hi>Eves, Ember-Days,</hi> &amp;c. for the Reaſons given in the <hi>Abridgment of Chriſtian Doctrin,</hi> Chap. IX. Prec. 2.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:45075:74"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXIII. <hi>Of</hi> Holy-Day Duties.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Keep Holy the Sabbath-Day, <hi>[and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Feaſts]</hi>
                  <bibl>Ex. <hi>20.8.</hi> [Lev. <hi>23.</hi> Num. <hi>28, and 29.</hi> Deuter. <hi>16. throughout.]</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BEſides reſting from Prophane Employments, and Servile La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the keeping of a Day Holy requires, 1. Holy Actions. 2. Holy Actors. And 3. A Holy Manner of Acting.</p>
            <p>§ I. Holy Actions and Exerciſes, are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Offering of, and Aſſiſting at the H. Sacrifice of the Maſs; for which ſee Chap. XIII.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Adminiſtring and Receiving of the <hi>Sacrament, John</hi> 7.22, 23. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7, 11. eſpecially of <hi>Penance,</hi> and the H. <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> for which ſee Chap. III. and Chap. V.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:45075:74"/>
            <p n="3">3. Preaching and Hearing <hi>Sermons, Mark</hi> 6.2. for which, ſee Chap. 14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Reading, Expounding, and Hearing the <hi>Scripture</hi> publicly, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16, <hi>&amp;c. Acts</hi> 13. <hi>Paſſim.</hi> c. 17. v. 2, 3. See Chap. 15.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Singing <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and Spiritual <hi>Canticles. Pſ.</hi> 91.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Making <hi>Offerings, Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Collections,</hi> for the Uſe of the Altar, <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Deut. 16.16, 17. Ex. 30.16. Prov. 3.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ecclus 35.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> for Maintenance of the Prieſt <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Ezek. 44.30. 1 Cor. 9.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>, and for Relief of the Poor
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Prov. 19.17. Tob. 4.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 16.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. c. 8, and c. 9. <hi>Paſſim.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Doing other <hi>Works of Mercy,</hi> both Spiritual and Corporal. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.10, <hi>&amp;c. Mark</hi> 3.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> c. 13. v. 16. <hi>John</hi> 5.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> c. 9. v. 14, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Note here, that on <hi>Sundays</hi> and Holy-days are allow'd,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Works of Neceſſity; as Dreſſing, and Cooking of Victuals, Looking
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:45075:75"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:45075:75"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:45075:76"/>and Foddering of Cattel, and ſuch like. <hi>Ex.</hi> 12.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.1, <hi>&amp;c. Mark</hi> 2.23, <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.15. <hi>John</hi> 5.8, <hi>&amp;c. Act.</hi> 1.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Such Innocent Recreations as do not Prejudice our Devotions, but refreſh our drooping Spirits, and enable us to <hi>ſerve our Lord in Cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</hi> Pſ. 99.1.</p>
            <p>§ II. The Qualities of Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and the Conditions of Acting Holily, are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>True Faith; without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> Heb. 11.6. And therefore, <hi>all that is not of Faith, is Sin;</hi> [i. e. is Unſanctified, and Unacceptable to God]. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A pure Heart, and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> becauſe <hi>every good Tree yields good Fruit; and if the Root be Holy, the Boughs alſo</hi> [are Holy]: <hi>But the evil Tree yields evil Fruit,</hi> and can no more yield good Fruit, than Thorns Grapes, or Thiſtles Figs. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 11.16. Hence <hi>the Sacrifices of the Wicked are abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to our Lord; the Vows</hi> [and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:45075:76"/>Devotions] <hi>of the Juſt are accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Prov. 15.8. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.27. <hi>Ecclus</hi> 34.23. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. This Diſpoſition of Heart and Conſcience God himſelf preſſes moſt energically, when he ſays, <hi>To what purpoſe do ye offer me the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of your Victims? I am full.—Who fought for theſe things at your Hands?—Offer Sacrifice no more in vain: Incenſe it Abomination to me. The Sabbath and other Feſtivals,</hi> [as Solemnized by you], <hi>I will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide; your Aſſemblies are wicked. My Soul hates your Solemnities; they are become tedious to me;—and when you ſhall multiply Prayers, I will not hear; for your Hands are full of Blood. Waſh you, be clean, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Evil of your Thoughts from my Eyes, ceaſe to do Perverſly, learn to do Good, ſeek Judgment, ſuccour the Oppreſſed,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 1.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See alſo <hi>c.</hi> 58. <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>For Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Clean and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpotted with God, is this; To viſit Pupils and Widows in their Tribulation, and to</hi>
[make and] <hi>keep ones ſelf unſpotted from this World.</hi> James 1.27.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:45075:77"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Perfect Charity;</hi> becauſe <hi>if I ſhould have all Faith—and have not Charity, I am nothing: And if I ſhould diſtribute all my Goods to the Poor,—and have not Charity, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits me nothing.</hi> 1 Cor. 13.2, 3.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>When you ſhall ſtand to Pray, forgive, if you have ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Man; that alſo your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is in Heaven, may forgive you your Sins.</hi> Mark 11.25. <hi>Forgive thy Neighbour hurting thee, and then ſhall thy Sins be looſed to thee, when thou prayeſt,</hi> &amp;c. Ecclus 28.2, &amp;c. <hi>But if you will not forgive Men, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will your Father forgive you your Offences.</hi> Mat. 6.15. And <hi>if thou offereſt thy Gifts at the Altar, and there remember'ſt, that thy Brother has ought againſt thee; leave there thy Offering before the Altar, and go firſt to be reconciled to thy Brother; and then coming, thou ſhalt offer thy Gift.</hi> Mat. 5.24, 25.</p>
            <p>Hence it appears, that Charity towards our Neighbour ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to accompany, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times take place of Divine Worſhip,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:45075:77"/>and God's more immediate Service: Becauſe <hi>to do Mercy and Judgment, does more pleaſe our Lord than Victims:</hi> And <hi>to love ones Neighbour, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is a greater thing, than all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locauſts and Sacrifices,</hi> [without Charity]. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.3. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.33. See alſo <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe three Conditions, (mention'd 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.) you muſt alſo have,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>A good Intention;</hi> to which the Apoſtle directs you, ſaying, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you do in Word, or in Work, do all things unto the Glory of God, and in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, giving Thanks to God and the Father by Him.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.31. Col. 3.17.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>True Devotion</hi> muſt inſpirit the whole Body of your Religious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and make you <hi>ſerve God with a perfect Heart, and a willing Mind.</hi> 1 Par. 28.9. <hi>For God is a Spirit; and they that adore him, muſt adore in Spirit and Truth,</hi> [John 4.24.] by offering <hi>Spiritual Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> [or Acts of Faith, Hope, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and other Interior Vertues] <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:45075:78"/>to God, thro' Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.5. without which, all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Reſpects and Signs of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are no better than Counterfeit Piety, and downright Hypocrifie. See <hi>Pſ.</hi> 77.36, 37. <hi>Ecclus</hi> 1.40. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.47.</p>
            <p>In fine. To keep <hi>Sundays</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Feaſts Holy, you muſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſerve God in Holineſs and Juſtice,</hi> but you muſt <hi>be alſo in all Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Holy.</hi> Luke 1.74, 75. and 1 Pet. 1.15.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>Of</hi> Working <hi>and</hi> Buſineſs.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Whatſoever you do, work it from the Heart, as to our Lord, and not to Men. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Col. 3.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>§ I. BEfore you take in Hand any Work or Buſineſs, make the Sign of the Croſs; and let it be your Intention and Aim to pleaſe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:45075:78"/>Him thereby, who ought to be the Beginning, Progreſs, and End of all your Actions, and for that Purpoſe ſay this ſhort Prayer:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord God of Mercy, give me Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,—from thy Holy Heavens, that ſhe may be with me, and labour with me; that I may know</hi> [and do] <hi>what is acceptable to thee.</hi> Wiſd. 9.</p>
            <p>§ II. <hi>In all thy Works be quick; and Infirmity ſhall not chance unto thee.</hi> Ecclus 31.27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Slothful Hand has wrought Poverty; the Hand of the Strong gets Riches.</hi> Prov. 10.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all thy Works be exquiſite,</hi> [or exact]; <hi>give no ſtain to thy Glory,</hi>
[thro' Negligence]. Ecclus 33.23.24.</p>
            <p>Hence it appears, that Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Diligent Labour is a great Friend to <hi>Health, Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Reputation;</hi> and it is as Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to Salvation, when Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Spiritual Recollection.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:45075:79"/>
            <p n="1">1. By calling to mind the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, or the Subject of your Mornings Meditation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By uſing Jaculatory Prayers, and Silent Elevation of the Heart to God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By Singing (with Heart and Voice) Pſalms, Hymns, and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Songs, whilſt you are at Work. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>§ III. When you have finiſhed your Work, offer it to God (its principal Author, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Labours and Pains undergone by Chriſt on Earth for us Men, and for our Salvation; and pray that what you have done may be acceptable to the Divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, thro' the Merits of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="chapter">
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:45075:79"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>Of</hi> Eating <hi>and</hi> Drinking.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Whether you Eat or Drink, or do any other thing, do all things to the Glory of God. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 10.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE firſt Chriſtians <hi>took their Meat with Joy and Simplicity</hi> (or Sincerity) <hi>of Heart, praiſing God.</hi> Acts 2.46. Do you in like manner: And,</p>
            <p>§ I. Before Meat <hi>ſay Grace,</hi> not for faſhion-ſake, and meerly out of Cuſtom, but with that inward De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and outward Reſpect, which is due to God, in whoſe preſence you are, and to whom you ſpeak; for this Leſſon Chriſt taught, when <hi>looking up to Heaven, he Bleſſed</hi> the Five Loaves and Two Fiſhes. <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.19.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> What Virtue the Bleſſing of our Meat has, you may ſee in the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:45075:80"/>Annotations of the <hi>Rhemes</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p>§ II. At Table, <hi>if thou be ſet in the midſt of many, ſtretch not forth thy Hand before them; neither do thou firſt ask to Drink. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, as a frugal Man, thoſe things, that are ſet before thee Leave off firſt, for Manners-ſake, and exceed not, leſt perhaps thou Offend. Watching, and Choler, and Torment to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſatiable Man: Sleep of Health is in a Man of ſpare Diet, and his Soul with him ſhall be delighted: Sober Drinking is Health to Soul and Body.</hi> Ecclus 31. <hi>paſſim. Eat what ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, but be not greedy in all Feaſting, and pour not out thy ſelf upon all Meat; for in many Meats there ſhall be Infirmity, and Greedineſs ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach even to Choler. Becauſe of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit many have Died; but he, that is abſtinent, ſhall add Life</hi> [both to Body and Soul]. <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.16. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus</hi> 37.32, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>§ III. After Meat <hi>ſay Grace</hi> again with Devotion and Reverence, and let thy Soul magnifie our Lord, for
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:45075:80"/>that <hi>he has filled the Hungry with Good Things,</hi> and thee amongſt the reſt, for no other end than that, <hi>when thou haſt Eaten and art Full, thou may'ſt Bleſs the Lord thy God.</hi> Luk. 1.53. Deut. 8.10.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>Of</hi> Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>If any Man think himſelf to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, not Bridling his Tongue, — this Man's Religion is Vain. But if any Man Offend not in Word; this is a Perfect Man. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jam. 1.26. c. 3. v. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>§ I. B Before you fall into Diſcourſe, make your Intention to keep up thereby true Charity, and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with your Neighbour, in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Imitation of Chriſt's Holy Converſation on Earth, with all ſorts of People: And then Pray thus;</p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:45075:81"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Set, O Lord, a Guard to my Mouth, and a Door to my Lips. Decline not my Heart into Words of Malice; that I fall not by Them, and my Tongue deſtroy me.</hi> Pſal. 140.3, 4. Ecclus 22.33.</p>
            <p>§ II. In Diſcourſe, ſpeak nothing but what is Good, <note place="margin">Eph. 4.29.</note> and Ediſying *, and better than Silence; in regard that, <hi>of every Idle Word that Men ſhall Speak, they ſhall give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in the Day of Judgment. For by thy Words thou ſhalt be Juſtified, and by thy Words thou ſhalt be Condemned.</hi> Mat. 12.36, 37. Wherefore <hi>He, that keeps his Mouth and his Tongue, keeps his Soul from Diſtreſſes; but he, that is unadviſed to ſpeak ſhall feel Evils.</hi> Prov. 13.3. c. 21. v. 23.</p>
            <p>Hence, that you may not Offend in Words, reflect now and then (whilſt you Diſcourſe) that God hears all you ſay, and that, one Day, you muſt render him an Account, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> If any one in your hearing utters Curſes, Oaths, Provoking
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:45075:81"/>Language, Detractions, Immodeſt Words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do not Smile, but Frown upon him: For, <hi>The North-Wind Diſſipates Rain, and a Sad look</hi> [Silences] <hi>the Tongue, that Detracts.</hi> Prov. 25.23. Therefore, in ſuch a Caſe, <hi>Anger is better than Laughter; becauſe by Sadneſs of the Countenance the Mind of the Offender is Corrected.</hi> Eccleſ. 7.4. whereas Smiling and Pleaſant Looks would Encourage him, and make you Guilty of his Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Haſt thou heard</hi> [unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably] <hi>a word againſt thy Neighbour? Let it Die together in thee</hi> [that is, never Divulge it while thou liveſt], <hi>truſting it will not burſt thee:—And believe not every</hi> [ſuch] <hi>Word</hi> [or Report]. <hi>For he, that gives Credit quickly, is light of Heart, and Sins againſt his own Soul.</hi> Ecclus 19.4.10.</p>
            <p>Again: If thou haſt been an Eye-Witneſs of thy Neighbour's failings, <hi>The things which thy Eyes have ſeen, utter not quickly in a Brawl; leſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards thou canſt not amend it, when
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:45075:82"/>thou haſt diſhonoured thy Friend,</hi> [Prov. 25.8.] by blemiſhing, or taking away his <hi>Good Name,</hi> a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity <hi>better than much Riches,</hi> [Prov. 22.1.] and harder to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored than they; for <hi>Volat irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabile Verbum:</hi> Yet Reſtored it muſt be, as much as poſſible; elſe the Sin of Defamation cannot be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, any more than the Sin of Theft; which is not forgiven, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Reſtitution be made.</p>
            <p>§ III. After Diſcourſe, call to mind, and be Sorry for, the Faults you have committed in Speaking; and, in Satisfaction for the ſame, puniſh your Tongue by Silence, or any other Mortification, for a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or longer ſpace of time; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Meaſure of your Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Read the <hi>Introduction to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Life.</hi> Part 3. Chap. 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="chapter">
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:45075:82"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>Of</hi> Recreation.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>A time to Laugh—and a time to Dance. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 3.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Service of Chriſt is a <hi>Yoke</hi> ſo <hi>Sweet,</hi> and a <hi>Burden</hi> ſo <hi>Light,</hi> [Mat. 11.30.] that even our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations and Paſtimes do pleaſe him, when they are Qualified with,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A good Intention,</hi> in ſeeking thereby to preſerve our Health, that we may be able to Serve God and our Neighbour, with greater Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> in obſerving what the Time, Place, and Perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and in complying therewith, as far as Modeſty, and a due Regard to the Preſence of God will Allow: but no farther: For the Apoſtle (admitting of no Diſpenſation in the Caſe) ſays, <hi>Let your Modeſty be known to all Men; our Lord is nigh.</hi> Phil. 4.5.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:45075:83"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Moderation,</hi> in Regulating our Affection and Attention to Play and Sport, ſo as not to make them Sinful and Vexations, nor to ſpend more time therein, than is Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the neceſſary Relaxation of Mind and Body, wearied with Prayer, Study or Labour. See more of this Duty in the <hi>Introduction to a Devout Life.</hi> Part III. Chap. XXXI, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>Of</hi> Family Duties.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Thus ſays the Lord—: Make your Ways Good, and your Studies; and I will dwell with you in this Place. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 7.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Well-Order'd Family is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Corporation, (or Body-Politick) conſiſting of a Head Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning, and of Members Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in a perfect Harmony of Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:45075:83"/>Intereſts, and Endeavours, for the Spiritual and Temporal Welfare of themſelves at Home, and the Edification of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Abroad.</p>
            <p>Now, that your Families may be ſuch, each Part thereof muſt know its proper Duty, and comply therewith, as follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Let Women be Subject to their Husbands as to our Lord; and as the Church is Subject to Chriſt, ſo alſo Women to their Husbands in all things: Becauſe the Man is Head of the Woman, as Chriſt is Head of the Church, his</hi> [Myſtical] <hi>Body.</hi> Eph. 5.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See alſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.9.</p>
            <p>Women likewiſe ought to <hi>Love their Husbands and Children, to be Wiſe, Chaſte, Sober, having a Care of the Houſe; to be Gentle,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that the Word of God be not Blaſphemed.</hi> Tit. 2.4, 5. See alſo <hi>Tob.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. throughout. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Husbands, love your Wives, as your own Bodies, as Chriſt alſo loved the Church; and be not bitter towards
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:45075:84"/>them: For no Man ever hated his own Fleſh, but he Nouriſhes and Cheriſhes it, as alſo Chriſt the Church.</hi> Eph. 5.25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Col. 3.19. See alſo 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Children, Honour your Parents, in Heart,</hi> by thinking well of them; <hi>in Word,</hi> by ſpeaking to and of them reſpectfully; <hi>in Work,</hi> by doing for them what you are able, <hi>and in all Patience,</hi> without Murmuring, or Uneaſineſs
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Tob. 4.3, 4. c. 10. v. 4. Ecclus 3. throughout. c. 7. v. 29, 30.</note>. <hi>Obey your Parents in all things, for this is well-pleaſing to our Lord</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Col. 3.20. Eph. 6.1, 2. Luk. 2.51.</note>. But to omit theſe Duties
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Deut. 27.16.</note>, or act contrary to them <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Deut. 21.18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Exod. 21.15, 17. Lev. 20.9. Prov. 15.5. c. 19. v. 26. c. 28. v. 24. c. 30. v. 17.</note>, is highly Offenſive, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely Puniſhable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>And you Fathers</hi> [and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers] <hi>Provoke not your Children to Anger,</hi>
[by unreaſonable Severity], <hi>that they become not Diſcouraged; but
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:45075:84"/>bring them up in the Diſcipline</hi> [or, Inſtruction] <hi>and Correction of our Lord</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="bottom">Eph. 6.4. Col. 3.21.</note>. That is, Teach them from their Infancy, to Fear and Serve God, and to Abſtain from Sin <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Gen. 18.18. Deut. 4.9. c. 11. v. 19. Tob. 1.10. c. 14. v. 10, 11, 17.</note>. And give them (when faulty) due Reprehenſions, and timely Chaſtiſement <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Prov. 13.24. c. 23. v. 13, 15. c. 29. v. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 17. Ecclus 7.25. and c. 30. <hi>paſſim.</hi> 1 Kin. 3.13.</note>.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Servants obey in all things your Maſters</hi> [and Miſtreſſes], <hi>not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to the Eye, as pleaſing Men, but in Simplicity</hi> [or Sincerity] <hi>of Heart, fearing God. Whatſoever you do, work it from the Heart, as to our Lord, and not to Men; knowing that you ſhall receive of our Lord the Reward of Inheritance</hi> [in Heaven]. <hi>Serve our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> [in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of your Maſters and Miſtreſſes], <hi>in all things pleaſing, not gainſaying; not defrauding, but in all things
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:45075:85"/>ſhewing good Faith</hi> [or Fidelity]. <hi>For he that does an Injury, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that which he has done <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtly; and there is no acception of Perſons with God.</hi> Col. 3.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Tit. 2.9. See alſo <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoever are Servants under Yoke, let them count their Maſters</hi> [tho' Unbelievers] <hi>worthy of all Honour; leſt the Name of our Lord and his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine be Blaſphem'd. But they, that have Faithful Maſters, let them not Contemn them, becauſe they are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; but Serve them rather, becauſe they are Faithful.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Servants, be Subject in all Fear to your Maſters, not only to the Good and Gentle, but alſo to the froward—. For, if doing well, you ſuſtain Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, ſuffering <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtly with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, this is acceptable before God. For unto this you are called; becauſe Chriſt alſo Suffered for us, leaving you an Example</hi> [of Innocent and Patient Suffering], <hi>that you may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Steps,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Pet. 2.18.</p>
            <p>See an Example of good Servants, under a good Maſter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.9.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:45075:85"/>and alſo under an ill one. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.38, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>And you Maſters</hi> [and Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes] <hi>that which is juſt and equal do to your Servants, forbearing Threats,</hi> [yet ſo as to keep them duly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, and under Subjection <note n="*" place="margin">Ecclus 11.7. <hi>c.</hi> 33. <hi>paſſim.</hi> Prov. 29.21.</note>] <hi>knowing that both their Lord and yours is in Heaven, and Acception of Perſons is not with him.</hi> Col. 4.1. Eph. 6.9. See alſo <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.17. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Job</hi> 31.13, <hi>&amp;c. Tob.</hi> 4, 15. <hi>Ecclus</hi> 4.35. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 22, 23. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſters and Miſtreſſes muſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe provide their Servants with Neceſſaries for Body and Soul, not only in Health, but alſo in Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, after the Example of the good Centurion. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, they muſt take Care they be inſtructed in the Myſteries of Faith, and ſee they Pray Morning and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening daily; Hear Maſs on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days</hi> and Holy-days; Confeſs and Receive Monthly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which Duties, <hi>if any one has not a Care of his own, and eſpecially of his Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:45075:86"/>he</hi> [I fear] <hi>has denied the Faith, and is worſe than an Infidel,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.8.</p>
            <p>But above all things, 'tis neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that Maſters and Miſtreſſes of Families be Vertuous themſelves, and imitate Holy <hi>David</hi> in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation and Government of his Houſe and Court, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 100. through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: Becauſe, <hi>what kind of Man the Ruler of the City</hi> [or Houſe] <hi>is, ſuch alſo are the Inhabitants therein.</hi> Ecclus 10.2. That is, if he be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and fears God, they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe do the ſame. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2. <hi>But a Prince</hi> [or Maſter of a Family] <hi>that gladly hears Words of Lying,</hi>
[Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Detraction, filthy Talk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] <hi>has all his Servants wicked.</hi> Prov. 19.12. For which Cauſe, <hi>a moſt ſevere Judgment ſhall paſs on them, that bear Rule.</hi> Wiſd. 6.6.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> Note here, that it is the Duty of Brothers and Siſters (as alſo of Fellow-Servants),</p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:45075:86"/>
            <p n="1">1. To live in Unity and Concord amongſt themſelves. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 132. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 25.1, 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To help and aſſiſt one another all they can. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To Bear with, and not Accuſe one another to their Parents, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Cauſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.2.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XXIX. <hi>A</hi> Morning Exerciſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The Wiſe Man will give his Heart to watch early unto our Lord that made him, and he will pray in the ſight of the Higheſt,—and will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for his Sins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ecclus 39.6,</hi> &amp;c.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHen it is time to Riſe, imagin you hear the Voice of Chriſt (your Heavenly Bridegroom) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you, <hi>Ariſe, my Love, my Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful one, and come:—Let thy Voice ſound in my Ears,</hi> &amp;c. Cant. 2.13,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:45075:87"/>14. And, in Compliance with ſo ſweet an Invitation, get up quickly to Converſe with him in Prayer, and let no ſluggiſh Delays bereave you of the Opportunity he offers you. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.3, 6.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing you do after you are up, Adore the Divine Majeſty on your Knees, by theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Give Thanks to God for all his Benefits in general, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly for preſerving you this Night from the Power of the Devil, and from ſudden Death, affording you more time to work your Salvation in, and to provide for Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Offer to God your Soul and Body, with all their Powers and Faculties; beſeeching him ſo to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs and govern them by his: Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Grace, that you may live, move, and act in and for him only, and may be entirely his, both in Time and Eternity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Divide the preſent Day into four Parts, allotting one to <hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> another to <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> a third to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:45075:87"/>
               <hi>Refection,</hi> and the laſt to <hi>Recreation;</hi> and forecaſt, that each of thoſe Affairs may be done in due Time, and after ſuch Manner, as this <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> appoints.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Ask Pardon of God for your paſt Sins, making a firm Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>end Him, either Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, or Venially, thro' deliberate Wilfulneſs and Malice, but to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all <hi>Vice;</hi> and eſpecially that, which you are moſt ſubject to, by avoiding <hi>ſuch and ſuch</hi> Occaſions th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f, and by doing <hi>ſuch and ſuch</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Vertue contrary thereto.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Beſeech God to ſtrengthen your good Purpoſes with his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Grace, and to aſſiſt you ſo, that whatever you ſhall think, ſay, do, and ſuffer this Day, may be for His greater Glory, your own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and your Neighbour's Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And to that Effect crave the Mediation of our Saviour, the Patronage and Interceſſion of the Bleſſed Virgin, of your good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, of your eſpecial Patrons, and of the Saint of the Day.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="chapter">
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:45075:88"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXX. <hi>An</hi> Evening Exerciſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>I meditated in the Night with my Heart, and I was exerciſed, and I ſwept my Spirit. </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſ. 76.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AT Night, before you go to Bed, place your ſelf on your Knees in the Preſence of God, and make the following Acts of Devotion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Give Thanks to God for all his Bleſſings and Benefits, (both Spiritual and Temporal) beſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed on you all the time of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, and eſpecially for thoſe you have this Day received.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Pray for Light to Diſcover, and Grace to Amend your Faults: As before, Chap. III. § I. N. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reflect from Hour to Hour ſince your laſt Examen, how you have behaved your ſelf at your <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions,</hi> in <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> at <hi>Table,</hi> in <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> and <hi>Recreation:</hi> How you have perform'd the <hi>Obligations</hi> of your State and Condition: What Uſe you have made of God's Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:45075:88"/>and of the Croſſes he has ſent you: How you have complied with your Mornings <hi>Reſolution</hi> of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Temptations and Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings you are moſt ſubject to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Offer to God all the Good you have done, acknowledging him to be the Sole Author of it. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. and be truly Penitent for the Sins you find your ſelf guilty of, tho' only Venial, and purpoſe to Amend them; leſt, neglecting ſmall Faults, you fall by little and little into great Diſorders, <hi>Ecclus</hi> 19.1. Make here the Act of Contrition, ſet down, Chap. III. § I. N. 4.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Take upon your ſelf ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior Mortification, as a Penance for your Sins, and implore the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mercy (thro' the Merits of Chriſt, and the Interceſſion of the B. Virgin, of your good Angel, of your eſpecial Patrons, and of the Saint of the Day) to pardon your paſt Offences, and preſerve you from future Failings, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward you may Live holily, and at laſt Die happily.</p>
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:45075:89"/>
            <p>And perform all theſe five Acts, as if you were to Die this very Night, and might have no other Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (beſides them) for Judgment.</p>
            <p n="*⁎*">
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> The laſt thing you do before you go to Bed, <hi>Read</hi> attentively the Subject of your next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings Meditation, or <hi>Chriſtian Thoughts</hi> for the enſuing Day of the Month, and entertain your Mind therewith until you fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, and as often as you awake in the Night; that whilſt you ſleep, your Heart may watch to God, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. and when you awake, he may be the Subject of your firſt Thoughts in the Morning. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 62.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.9. And that, whether you watch; or ſleep, you may live together with Chriſt in God. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.10.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>And now I have ſet before you, in the foregoing Chapters, ſuch a Syſtem of Religious and Moral Duties, as I intended, I ſhall here take my leave, and bid you fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel in the following Terms.</p>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:45075:89"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I beſeech you, Brethren, that you walk worthy of the Vocation, in which you are called, with all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and Mildneſs, with Patience, ſupporting one another in Charity, careful to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in the Bond of Peace,</hi> &amp;c. Eph. 4.1. &amp;c. <hi>Converſe ye worthy of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 1.26. <hi>And according to him that has called you, the Holy One,</hi> [that is, according to Chriſt], <hi>be you alſo in all Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Holy; becauſe it is written, you ſhall be Holy, becauſe I am Holy. And in fear</hi> [and Expectation of the Day of Judgment] <hi>converſe ye the time of your ſojourning.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For Good and Holy Converſation is the only way to ſave our own Souls, and the beſt Argument we can uſe for Confuting and Converting the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries of our Profeſſion, as you may ſee, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.7, 8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 16.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>that you may be perfect and entire, failing in nothing.</hi> Jam. 1.4. At the end of each Month, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:45075:90"/>how you have paſſed it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſee whether you have gain'd or loſt Ground in your Way to Heaven, during ſo conſiderable a part of your Time: If you have gain'd, thank God for your Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement in Vertue: If you have loft, confound your ſelf for your Backwardneſs, and reſolve to live better the next Month. Becauſe He goes back, who advances not in Vertue; and whoſoever pretends not to become better, leaves off be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 83.8. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.11. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.52.</p>
            <p>A like Review of the whole Year ought to be made at the end thereof, according to the Form pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the 5th Part of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction to a Devout Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quod fui, Domine, ignoſce: quod ſum Corrige: quod ero dirige: ne idem momentum ſit mihi &amp; Paenae Initium, &amp; Vitae</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45075:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
